<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Startwords</title><link>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/</link><description>Recent content on Startwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data Beyond Vision</title><link>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/</guid><description>&lt;p>How do we share tangible objects in a visual medium? We present, describe, use words, pictures, diagrams, &lt;em>show&lt;/em> … fail.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Body As Data</title><link>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/the-body-as-data/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/the-body-as-data/</guid><description>&lt;p>When I was growing up I liked to read about dying children. I’m not talking about the Victorian orphan kind of dying either, not the dying of storybooks, but children (well, teenagers) who were terminally ill.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About</title><link>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/about/</guid><description>startword, n. (computer science) A string of letters that identifies the beginning of a valid sequence in a specified language. (literature) The first appearance of a genre in print. Startwords is a research periodical irregularly published by the Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton. More formal than a blog yet more speculative and process-based than a peer-reviewed journal, Startwords is a forum for experimental humanities scholarship. Embedded code, data physicalizations, and emerging forms of project documentation are explored through writing that is creative, conversational, exploratory, essayistic, data-driven, and academically rigorous.</description></item></channel></rss>