<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.119.0">Hugo</generator><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="html"/><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/index.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="rss"/><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" title="Atom"/><updated>2023-10-04T19:50:23+00:00</updated><rights>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</rights><author><name>Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton</name><email>cdh-info@princeton.edu</email></author><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/</id><entry><title type="html">Of Sonorous Medieval Chinese Texts and NLP Model Training</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/sonorous-medieval/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/sonorous-medieval/</id><author><name>Nick Budak</name></author><author><name>Gian Rominger</name></author><published>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T15:48:34-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A distinctive set of challenges arises when training machines to process a historical language, especially one that was last spoken two millennia ago. One of the core issues embedded in natural language processing (NLP) models for historical languages is the acute lack of annotated datasets, despite the long scholastic and exegetical traditions for some of these languages. This article focuses on a specific historical language with an extensive commentarial tradition: premodern forms of Chinese spanning the Warring States (476&ndash;221 BCE) and early imperial (221 BCE&ndash;220 CE) periods. By highlighting the challenges of this particular language and our approach to building an NLP model that aims to overcome these difficulties, we will argue how textual commentaries from the medieval period can be used for NLP model training purposes.</p>
<p>It may at first appear that the goal of an NLP model for historical languages consists in building the largest model and extracting the highest accuracy score from it. Conventional wisdom holds that larger is better when it comes to datasets, particularly for modern languages, in order to build a seemingly complete picture of the target language.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> It may be equally tempting to rely on the currently dominant focus in NLP by building contextual representations of meaning in the form of word embeddings. (This is nowhere more apparent than in the currently ubiquitous assertion that &ldquo;attention is all you need&rdquo; in the Transformer architecture.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>)</p>
<p>But when approaching a language like Old Chinese, the architecture and hyperparameters<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> of the model itself are, at best, of secondary concern. In reality, the bulk of time and effort is devoted to questions of data curation and the painstaking labor necessary to identify and annotate the unique qualities of this language.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> As we will see, the question of meaning in context is far more complex than counting the collection of words surrounding the one we happen to be interested in, as the Transformer architecture would imply. Additional considerations include questions like: Who will curate the corpus of texts? How will this corpus be made machine readable? What portions will be used for the training and evaluation of the model?</p>
<p>In the project we introduce here<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> &mdash; the result of a collaboration between a software engineer and a philologist &mdash; we generate an NLP model based on data derived from premodern Chinese annotations. In many ways, we have found that questions facing the twenty-first-century researcher equipped with large language models and Python libraries echo those of the sixth-century scholar using brush and ink.</p>
<h2 id="i">I.</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s begin by describing some of the distinctive features of Old Chinese, a language that survives in a corpus of ancient texts that can be dated to the centuries preceding and during the first dynasties of Imperial China, or roughly 476 BCE to 220 CE. These written texts survive either as documents that were transmitted and copied through the millennia, or as recently excavated or otherwise surfaced manuscripts.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup></p>
<p><figure>
<div class="deepzoom shadow" id="openseadragon-0" style="height: 50em" aria-label="Interactive zoomable viewer showing four wooden tablets in clerical script."></div>
<script>
    window.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        OpenSeadragon({
            id: "openseadragon-0",
            prefixUrl: "https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/openseadragon@2.4/build/openseadragon/images/",
            preserveViewport: true,
            visibilityRatio:    1,
            minZoomLevel:       1,
            defaultZoomLevel:   1,
            gestureSettingsMouse: { scrollToZoom: false },
            tileSources: "https:\/\/ids.si.edu\/ids\/iiif\/FS-F1981.4a-e\/info.json",
        });
    });
</script>

    <figcaption><p><strong>Figure 1.</strong> Four Wooden Tablets in clerical script, <a href="https://asia-archive.si.edu/object/F1981.4a-e/">Freer Gallery of Art</a> (accessed August 20, 2023).</p></figcaption>

</figure>


<figure class="deepzoom-preview">
    <img src="https://ids.si.edu/ids/iiif/FS-F1981.4a-e/full/1500,/0/default.jpg" alt="four wooden tablets in clerical script." loading="lazy"/>
    <figcaption>
    
    <p><strong>Figure 1.</strong> Four Wooden Tablets in clerical script, <a href="https://asia-archive.si.edu/object/F1981.4a-e/">Freer Gallery of Art</a> (accessed August 20, 2023).</p>
    
    <p><small>The online version of this essay includes an interactive deep zoom viewer displaying a high resolution version of this image.</small></p></figcaption>
</figure>

<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE. Interactive zoomable viewer showing four wooden tablets in clerical script.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 1.</strong> Four Wooden Tablets in clerical script.
| ATTRIBUTION: Freer Gallery of Art
| LINK: <a href="https://asia-archive.si.edu/object/F1981.4a-e/">https://asia-archive.si.edu/object/F1981.4a-e/</a>
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>For heuristic purposes, we use the term &ldquo;Old Chinese&rdquo; for the underlying language, and like other stages of the Chinese language family, it is marked by the usage of Chinese characters or glyphs. As a writing system, Chinese glyphs have remained largely stable from the Han dynasty (202 BCE&ndash;220 CE) to the present day, with the greatest change occurring in 1956 in the form of the People&rsquo;s Republic of China&rsquo;s script reform and the introduction of simplified characters. A text from the early twentieth century may thus on the surface appear indistinguishable from a genuinely ancient piece of writing. This is in particular the case due to the venerated status of a few classical texts, largely from pre-imperial China, which served as models for later literary forms of writing up until the twentieth century. Existing NLP models for premodern Chinese assume a seemingly enduring and unchanging use of the written language, grouped under the notions of &ldquo;Literary&rdquo; or &ldquo;Classical Chinese&rdquo; (<em>wen yan</em> 文言 and <em>gudian Hanyu</em> 古典漢語).<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> But this understanding of a never-changing and static language is not just ahistorical and incorrect; it also misses the point of what Chinese glyphs inherently represent: like other forms of writing, they are a conventionalized system used to represent the dynamic utterances of a language.</p>
<p>In this sense, <em>sound</em> is crucial to reading early Chinese texts, and the content of these texts is often inextricably linked to the topic of sound: the Chinese classics and texts of the genre of Masters literature (<em>zi shu</em> 子書) are astoundingly rich in puns, rhymes, and wordplay.<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup></p>
<p>Often, these texts present themselves as representing speech, and many of them may have had performative functions and poetic features that remain largely hidden, simply due to the fact that the Chinese writing system only poorly reflects its phonological features.<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup> The conceit of continuous access to written heritage is thus a mirage.</p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    The sound system of the language underwent significant changes even as its graphemes remained static.
</blockquote>
<p>So how can we access the sounds of a language that lost its last native speakers millennia ago? Chinese &mdash; like other languages &mdash; has changed over time. More specifically, the sound system of the language underwent significant changes even as its graphemes remained static. Old Chinese phonology is therefore a reconstructed system, derived from documentary evidence. In this context, heteronyms pose an issue also present in modern forms of Chinese: characters whose pronunciation and meaning change based on context, defying attempts to convert them directly into phonemes.<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup> One of the best-known examples of such a homograph is the glyph 樂, which can be read &mdash; depending on context &mdash; as either <em>lè</em> (&ldquo;joy&rdquo;) or <em>yuè</em> (&ldquo;music&rdquo;) in modern Standard Chinese, which can be reconstructed as *[rˤ]awk or *[ŋ]ˤrawk in Old Chinese.</p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig2">
<table class="side-scroll">
  <caption>
    <b>Figure 2.</b> Heteronyms in ancient and modern languages.
  </caption>
  <tbody>
    <tr class="languages">
      <td rowspan="2"></td>
      <th colspan="2">Old Chinese</th>
      <th colspan="2">US English</th>
    </tr>
    <tr class="words">
      <td colspan="2" lang="zh">樂</td>
      <td colspan="2">excuse</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="gloss">
      <th scope="row">meaning</th>
      <td>music</td>
      <td>joy</td>
      <td>to forgive</td>
      <td>justification</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="translit">
      <th scope="row">sound</th>
      <td>*[ŋ]ˤrawk</td>
      <td>*[r]ˤawk</td>
      <td>/ɪksˈkjuz/</td>
      <td>/ɪksˈkjus/</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

</div>
<p>Another problem is the graphic variation common in early forms of Chinese, especially prior to the large-scale standardization of orthography during the third to first centuries BCE. In other words, while one glyph could be pronounced multiple ways, the <em>same</em> word could additionally be written with different glyphs in ancient texts. The same textual passage &mdash; say, a line of a poem &mdash; could hence be written with rather different glyphs.<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> Thus without a model that incorporates homographs, graphic variation, and other contextual understandings of phonology, the (often quite complex) puns, rhymes, and wordplays of ancient texts remain hidden below their surface forms. More crucially, however, unstandardized recurrences &mdash; not just of named entities, but of entire parallel passages &mdash; may go unnoticed.<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup></p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig3">
<p class="caption">
  <b>Figure 3.</b> Textual parallels across three early Chinese texts, 
  both on a grapheme level and on that of phonology alone. The phrase 
  “he did not speak for three years” (solid underline) occurs across these 
  texts, using the same glyphs. Passages with wavy and dotted underlines 
  utilize different glyphs, but largely overlap on a phonological level.
</p>
<p class="caption">
  For these examples, see David Schaberg, “Speaking of Documents: 
  <em>Shu</em> Citations in Warring States Texts,” in <cite>Origins of Chinese Political 
  Philosophy: Studies in the Composition and Thought of the ‘Shangshu’
  (Classic of Documents)</cite>, ed. Martin Kern and Dirk Meyer (Leiden: Brill, 2017), 320–59.
</p>
<blockquote>
  <div class="source">
    <p lang="zh">
      作其即位，乃或<span class="g2">亮陰</span>，<span class="par"
        >三年不言</span
      >。其惟不言，言乃<span class="g1">雍</span>。
    </p>
  </div>
  <div class="notes">
    <p class="translation">
      At the start, when he ascended the throne, then, it is said,
      <span class="g2">the light was obscured</span> and
      <span class="par">for three years he did not speak</span>. His
      acting without words was thus <span class="g1">harmonious</span>.
    </p>
    <footer>
      From the chapter “Do not Indulge” (<i>wu yi </i><span lang="zh">毋逸</span>), from the
      <cite class="book">Book of Documents</cite> (<cite class="book">Shang shu</cite> <span lang="zh">尚書</span>)
    </footer>
  </div>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  <div class="source">
    <p lang="zh">
      書云：高宗<span class="par">三年不言</span>，言乃<span class="g1"
        >歡</span
      >。
    </p>
  </div>
  <div class="notes">
    <p class="translation">
      The <cite class="book">Documents</cite> state: ‘Gaozong
      <span class="par">did not speak for three years</span>. When he did
      speak, he was <span class="g1">joyous</span>.’
    </p>
    <footer>
      From the chapter “Tan Gong II” (<span lang="zh">檀弓下</span>), from the
      <cite class="book">Book of Rites</cite> (<cite class="book">Li ji</cite> <span lang="zh">禮記</span>)
    </footer>
  </div>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  <div class="source">
    <p lang="zh">
      高宗，天子也。即位<span class="g2">諒闇</span>，<span class="par"
        >三年不言</span
      >。
    </p>
  </div>
  <div class="notes">
    <p class="translation">
      Gaozong was Heaven’s Son. When he ascended the throne,
      <span class="g2">it was truly dark</span>, and
      <span class="par">for three years he did not speak</span>.
    </p>
    <footer>
      From <cite class="book">Master Lü's Spring and Autumn Annals</cite> 6/2 (<cite class="book">Lü shi chunqiu</cite> <span lang="zh">呂氏春秋</span>)
    </footer>
  </div>
</blockquote>

</div>
<p>Fortunately, previous scholarship has grappled with many of these issues, and historical secondary sources offer an intriguing source of semi-structured data in the form of commentaries, dictionaries, and other scholarly work. The <em>Qieyun</em> 切韻, a rhyme dictionary compiled in 601 CE, is an important example: it records normative reading practices that represent a compromise between then-current Northern and Southern styles of pronouncing of glyphs in the classical texts from early China. Modern reconstructions of Old Chinese phonology draw heavily on the <em>Qieyun</em> and its later redactions, as these texts provide a formal structure and closed system of phonological distinctions for the underlying Middle Chinese.</p>

<blockquote class="pull right">
    The often quite complex puns, rhymes, and wordplays of ancient texts remain hidden below their surface forms.
</blockquote>
<p>The stability of the script also led to problems over time. In China, generations of medieval and early modern writers were trained to memorize the Odes of the ancient <em>Shi jing</em> 詩經 &mdash; called the <em>Classic of Poetry</em> for a good reason &mdash; but they soon grappled with the fact that these texts largely did not to rhyme when read aloud. The underlying phonology had changed.<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup></p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig4">
<p class="caption">
  <b>Figure 4.</b> Selected lines of the poem “Guan ju” <span lang="zh">《關雎》</span> from the
  <cite class="book">Classic of Poetry</cite> (<cite class="book">Shi jing</cite> <span lang="zh">詩經</span>),
  expressed through glyphs, Old Chinese and Middle Chinese phonology, and the pinyin romanization system of
  Standard Mandarin Chinese. Rhyming words are underlined with their matching vowel sounds glowing; note in
  particular the disappearing rhymes in selection 1 from Middle
  Chinese to Modern Chinese, and in selection 2 from Old Chinese
  to Middle Chinese.
</p>
<table>
  <caption>
    1. Guan-guan [goes] the osprey, on the river’s islet.
    <p class="sr-only">Rhyming “u” sounds at the end of the two four-character lines are preserved in Old Chinese and Middle Chinese, but in Modern Chinese the selection has no rhyming words.</p>
  </caption>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th scope="col" aria-label="Character"></th>
      <th scope="col">Old Chinese</th>
      <th scope="col">Middle Chinese</th>
      <th scope="col">Modern Chinese</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">關</td>
      <td>*k<sup>ʕ</sup>ro[n]</td>
      <td>kwaen</td>
      <td class="pinyin">guān</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">關</td>
      <td>*k<sup>ʕ</sup>ro[n]</td>
      <td>kwaen</td>
      <td class="pinyin">guān</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">雎</td>
      <td>*[tsh]a</td>
      <td>tshjo</td>
      <td class="pinyin">jū</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">鳩</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*[k](r)<span class="vowel">u</span></td>
      <td class="rhyme">kj<span class="vowel">u</span>w</td>
      <td class="pinyin">jiū</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">在</td>
      <td>*[dz]<sup>ʕ</sup>әʔ</td>
      <td>dzojX</td>
      <td class="pinyin">zài</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">河</td>
      <td>*[C.g]<sup>ʕ</sup>aj</td>
      <td>ha</td>
      <td class="pinyin">hé</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">之</td>
      <td>*tә</td>
      <td>tsyi</td>
      <td class="pinyin">zhī</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">洲</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*t<span class="vowel">u</span></td>
      <td class="rhyme">tsy<span class="vowel">u</span>w</td>
      <td class="pinyin">zhōu</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<table>
  <caption>
    2. Seeking her, [he] did not find [her]; Waking and sleeping, he thinks longingly [of her].
    <p class="sr-only">Rhyming “ə” sounds in the final two words of both lines appear in Old Chinese, but in both Middle Chinese and Modern Chinese the poem has no rhyming sounds.</p>
  </caption>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th scope="col" aria-label="Character"></th>
      <th scope="col">Old Chinese</th>
      <th scope="col">Middle Chinese</th>
      <th scope="col">Modern Chinese</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">求</td>
      <td>*g(r)u</td>
      <td>gjuw</td>
      <td class="pinyin">qiú</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">之</td>
      <td>*tә</td>
      <td>tsyi</td>
      <td class="pinyin">zhī</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">不</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*p<span class="vowel">ə</span></td>
      <td>pjuw</td>
      <td class="pinyin">bù</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">得</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*t<sup>ʕ</sup><span class="vowel">ә</span>k</td>
      <td>tok</td>
      <td class="pinyin">dé</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">寤</td>
      <td>*ŋ<sup>ʕ</sup>a-s</td>
      <td>nguH</td>
      <td class="pinyin">wù</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td lang="zh">寐</td>
      <td>*mi[t]-s</td>
      <td>mjijH</td>
      <td class="pinyin">mèi</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">思</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*[s]<span class="vowel">ə</span></td>
      <td>si</td>
      <td class="pinyin">sī</td>
    </tr>
    <tr class="rhyme-line">
      <td lang="zh">服</td>
      <td class="rhyme">*[b]<span class="vowel">ə</span>k</td>
      <td>bjuwk</td>
      <td class="pinyin">fú</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

</div>
<h2 id="ii">II.</h2>
<p>Instead of annotating early Chinese texts manually to disambiguate these problems in reading a given passage, we decided to rely entirely on traditional Chinese scholarship on the ancient classics as a data source. In order for such premodern scholarship to be fruitfully utilized as a data source for NLP training purposes, and for such scholarship to address the problem of disambiguating different readings, several criteria must be met. Initially, the source text must provide phonological data as explicitly as possible &mdash; after all, our aim is to assemble a language model that meaningfully reflects not just the glyphs used, but also their underlying sounds. Secondly, older scholarly sources are better; however, unlike Middle Chinese, which offers a convenient textual starting point in the form of the <em>Qieyun,</em> approaching Old Chinese inevitably includes Middle Chinese data, given the significantly closer temporal proximity of medieval scholars &mdash; like the <em>Qieyun</em>&rsquo;s compilator Lu Fayan 陸法言 (ca. 581&ndash;618) &mdash; to the ancient classics. Thirdly, data is needed on pronunciations given in realistic contexts in order to overcome the problems of homographs and graphic variation. That way, a future model of ours can use this contextual information to improve its accuracy.</p>
<p>One early work appears to fulfill all of these criteria: the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> 經典釋文, completed in 583 CE by the scholar Lu Deming 陸德明 (d. 630). This monumental commentary provides tens of thousands of phonological, semantic, and bibliographic notes across a representative selection of sixteen ancient classical texts. The material being annotated is broad, ranging from poetic odes (the <em>Shi jing</em>) and historical chronicles (the <em>Chunqiu</em> 春秋 and its commentaries) to an ancient dictionary (the <em>Erya</em> 爾雅). Lu Deming&rsquo;s analysis draws from some 230 sources, some of which are not attested in any other work.<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup></p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    Lu Deming’s meticulous attention to detail produced what is effectively a machine-readable dataset millennia before such machines would exist.
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> wrestles with some of the same problems we face today, as its commentarial style disambiguates homographs and the inconsistencies presented by graphic variation in the texts it studies. While Lu Deming lived during a tumultuous period that spanned multiple imperial dynasties and spawned many competing schools of thought on how the classics should be read, his explanatory annotations eventually received official recognition and earned him posthumous fame and a commendation from emperor Taizong 太宗 (598&ndash;649) of the Tang dynasty 唐 (618&ndash;907 CE).<sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup></p>
<p>The <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> utilizes a relatively novel form of commentary: rather than reproducing the source text in full, it instead lists only what we call headwords, which are short excerpts, ranging from single glyphs to short passages. Each of these short sequences of glyphs is paired with a corresponding annotation. Each headword is distinctive enough to be matched to its location in the full text of the original source. The <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> is thus a semi-structured text that provides sequences of glyphs that can be located in specific contexts in the source texts, and supplies annotations for a specific glyph in the relevant sequence.<sup id="fnref:16"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup> By essentially compressing the source texts in this way, the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> manages to cover almost 900,000 characters of primary-source material in just over 100,000 characters of excerpt. The resulting &ldquo;compression ratio&rdquo; is 13:1.<sup id="fnref:17"><a href="#fn:17" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup></p>
<p><figure>
<div class="deepzoom shadow" id="openseadragon-8" style="height: 40em" aria-label="Interactive zoomable viewer showing folio of vertical Chinese script with large characters and half-width notes in a smaller font size."></div>
<script>
    window.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        OpenSeadragon({
            id: "openseadragon-8",
            prefixUrl: "https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/openseadragon@2.4/build/openseadragon/images/",
            preserveViewport: true,
            visibilityRatio:    1,
            minZoomLevel:       1,
            defaultZoomLevel:   1,
            gestureSettingsMouse: { scrollToZoom: false },
            tileSources: "https:\/\/ids.lib.harvard.edu\/ids\/iiif\/16417478\/info.json",
        });
    });
</script>

    <figcaption><p><strong>Figure 5.</strong> Folio from 1680 printing of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>, with headwords rendered in large glyphs, and annotations immediately following in half-width running in two columns; from <a href="https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:16416657$80i">Harvard-Yenching Library, Harvard University</a> (accessed September 3, 2023)</p></figcaption>

</figure>


<figure class="deepzoom-preview">
    <img src="https://ids.lib.harvard.edu/ids/iiif/16417478/full/1500,/0/default.jpg" alt="Folio view of vertical Chinese script with large characters and half-width notes in a smaller font size" loading="lazy"/>
    <figcaption>
    
    <p><strong>Figure 5.</strong> Folio from 1680 printing of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>, with headwords rendered in large glyphs, and annotations immediately following in half-width running in two columns; from <a href="https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:16416657$80i">Harvard-Yenching Library, Harvard University</a> (accessed September 3, 2023)</p>
    
    <p><small>The online version of this essay includes an interactive deep zoom viewer displaying a high resolution version of this image.</small></p></figcaption>
</figure>

<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE. Interactive zoomable viewer showing folio of vertical Chinese script with large characters and half-width notes in a smaller font size.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 5.</strong> Folio from 1680 printing of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>, with headwords rendered in large glyphs, and annotations immediately following in half-width running in two columns.
| ATTRIBUTION: Harvard-Yenching Library, Harvard University
| LINK: <a href="https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:16416657$80i">https://iiif.lib.harvard.edu/manifests/view/drs:16416657$80i</a>
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>While earlier dictionaries primarily glossed glyphs by providing similar-sounding glyphs to indicate their reading, the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> employed a rather novel way of indicating pronunciation: the <em>fanqie</em> 反切 system.<sup id="fnref:18"><a href="#fn:18" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup> This method of noting a glyph&rsquo;s phonology separates a syllable into its initial consonant on the one hand, and its rhyme and tone on the other. No longer constrained to providing pronunciations by finding a word that overlapped exactly in sound, the <em>fanqie</em> system allowed scholars such as Lu Deming to instead choose common graphs for the initial and rhyme plus tone independently. Given the reliance on the Chinese script, both initial and rhyme plus tone are expressed through a common glyph.</p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig6">
<div>
  <aside class="card">
  <header>Say <em>east</em> in Middle Chinese</header>
  <p class="large">
    <audio src="assets/tuwng.mp3"></audio>
    <button class="play" aria-label="listen to tuwng"></button>
    <span class="tek" lang="zh">東</span> tuwŋ</p>
  <p class="large"><span class="tek"><span lang="zh">德</span> +</span> <span lang="zh">紅</span> = <span lang="zh">東</span></p>
  <p class="phonetic"><span class="tek">
    <audio src="assets/tok.mp3"></audio><button class="play" aria-label="listen to tok"></button>
    t<span class="fade">ok</span></span>
    <audio src="assets/huwng.mp3"></audio><button class="play" aria-label="listen to huwng"></button>
    <span class="fade">h</span>uwŋ</p>
  </aside>
  <aside class="card">
    <header>Say <em>fight</em> in English</header>
    <p class="large">
      <audio src="assets/fight.mp3"></audio>
      <button class="play" aria-label="listen to fight"></button>
      <span class="fish">Fight</span> /fʌɪt/</p>
    <p class="large"><span class="fish">Fish +</span> light = fight</p>
    <p class="phonetic">
      <audio src="assets/fish.mp3"></audio><button class="play" aria-label="listen to fish"></button>
      <span class="fish">/f<span class="fade">ɪʃ</span>/</span>
      <audio src="assets/light.mp3"></audio><button class="play" aria-label="listen to light"></button>
     /<span class="fade">l</span>ʌɪt/</span>
    </p>
  </aside>
  <p class="caption"><b>Figure 6.</b> How the <em>fanqie</em> pronunciation system works</p>
</div>

</div>
<p>In this way, the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> is both comprehensive and concise in the way it provides phonological data in context. We believe it provides enough data to train an NLP model. The key question is then how to extract this data; while Lu Deming&rsquo;s meticulous attention to detail produced what is effectively a machine-readable dataset millennia before such machines would exist, adjusting the specific format still necessitates significant labor on our part.</p>
<h2 id="iii">III.</h2>
<p>The first obstacle we face in turning the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> into phonological training data is the need for a digitized version of this text. Fortunately, the Kanseki Repository, an online database of premodern Chinese texts, offers digitized editions of over nine thousand works, including the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> and the source texts it annotates.<sup id="fnref:19"><a href="#fn:19" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup> This repository usually offers multiple editions for each work, in addition to interpretive versions that attempt to merge the editions into a state-of-the-art copy of the text. In keeping with the repository&rsquo;s permissive licensing and spirit of &ldquo;electronic texts by researchers, for researchers,&rdquo; our own work is available under an open license and published on GitHub.<sup id="fnref:20"><a href="#fn:20" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup></p>
<p>Only with such a digitized version of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> and related texts can we approach the key question of how to extract useful phonological data from Lu Deming&rsquo;s commentary. A look at the content of this text highlights why this question is crucial: while close to one-third of the roughly 55,000 notes in the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> consist solely of a reading gloss (thus providing a reading aid to indicate pronunciation), the remainder is more complex and addresses multiple concerns. Some annotations feature semantic glosses, and others highlight instances in which additional works reproduce a glyph differently or include citations to the interpretations of other scholars. Many annotations combine these different elements. More importantly, the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> contains yet another form of abridgement: instead of reproducing the same annotation multiple times, the text attaches qualifiers to indicate that a given reading applies every time a human reader encounters the given string of glyphs in a specific section of the source text. These qualifiers act as multipliers for the data, effectively extending the commentary to cover whole swaths of text not explicitly noted elsewhere.</p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig7">
<p class="caption">
  <b>Figure 7.</b> An example showing the richness of annotations in the <cite class="book">Jingdian Shiwen</cite> <span lang="zh">經典釋文</span>, and the common patterns they take.
</p>
<div class="text">
  <div class="head segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">相摩</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="label">Headword</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="graphic segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">本又作磨</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">Edition[s] also write it [<span lang="zh">摩</span>] as “<span lang="zh">磨</span>”</div>
      <div class="label">Graphic</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="phon segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">末何反</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">it is pronounced like <span lang="zh">末</span> + <span lang="zh">何</span> [ma]</div>
      <div class="label">Phonological</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="person segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">京</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">Jing</div>
      <div class="label">Person</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="semantic segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">云相磑切也</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">says that it means “milled against one another”</div>
      <div class="label">Semantic</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="phon segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">磑音古代反</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">“mill” <span lang="zh">[磑]</span> is pronounced like <span lang="zh">古</span> + <span lang="zh">代</span> [gojH]</div>
      <div class="label">Phonological</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="person segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">馬</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">Ma</div>
      <div class="label">Person</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="semantic segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">云摩切也</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">says that it means “ground up”</div>
      <div class="label">Semantic</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="person segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">鄭</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">Zheng[’s]</div>
      <div class="label">Person</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="work segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">注禮記</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">commentary on the <cite class="book">Book of Rites</cite></div>
      <div class="label">Work</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="semantic segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">云迫也</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">says that it means “compelled”</div>
      <div class="label">Semantic</div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="phon segment">
    <div class="source"><p lang="zh">迫音百</p></div>
    <div class="notes">
      <div class="translation">“compel” <span lang="zh">[迫]</span> is pronounced like <span lang="zh">百</span> [paek]</div>
      <div class="label">Phonological</div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>

</div>
<p>Our approach to handling these complexities is to train a special-purpose model equipped to parse the terse style of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>&rsquo;s highly structured annotations. We use the Prodigy annotation tool to note parts of speech and syntactic relationships in the commentary, and pair it with the spaCy NLP library to create a custom processing pipeline.<sup id="fnref:21"><a href="#fn:21" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup> By applying this micro-model to the annotation corpus, each individual reading gloss can be extracted and paired with qualifying data. A notable side effect of this approach is that it simultaneously produces a citation network dataset: references that the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> makes to other texts and authors can be extracted from the text along with phonological data.</p>
<p>Once we have extracted all of the relevant phonological data, the task still remains to transform it into reconstructed forms of first Middle Chinese, and then Old Chinese. This is a process involving a few considerations: while the reading glosses of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> &mdash; given directly and in <em>fanqie</em> form &mdash; reflect Middle Chinese, these glosses can also be used to make some inferences about the earlier Old Chinese. In order to strengthen these inferences, we use the reading glosses provided by the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> as disambiguation data and cross-reference these glosses with both contemporary rhyme dictionaries like the <em>Qieyun</em> and modern historical linguistic data (primarily William H. Baxter and Laurent Sagart&rsquo;s 2014 reconstruction of Old Chinese<sup id="fnref:22"><a href="#fn:22" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup>). The overall goal is to stay as true as possible to the source material: if the rhyming portion of a syllable can be determined, but its initial consonant is represented ambiguously in the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>, we attempt to capture that ambiguity in the data.</p>

<blockquote class="pull right">
    We borrow a strategy from the modern science of bioinformatics: specifically, genetic algorithms designed to find the best overall “alignment” of sequences of amino acids (or, in our case, sequences of glyphs).
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, in order to create a fully machine-readable dataset, we reunite the annotations of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> with the full text of the classical works that it annotates. Because of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>&rsquo;s tendency to economize on space by attaching comments to excerpted headwords, identifying the precise locations in the text where the headwords occur is necessary to match the annotations to their original context. To do this, we borrow a strategy from the modern science of bioinformatics: specifically, genetic algorithms designed to find the best overall &ldquo;alignment&rdquo; of sequences of amino acids (or, in our case, sequences of glyphs).<sup id="fnref:23"><a href="#fn:23" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup> Once the headwords have been matched to their original positions in the source text, we copy over their corresponding phonological data to obtain a dataset of reading glosses in their historical context.</p>
<p>In using historical secondary sources for training an NLP model, we have found that even sources compiled millennia ago can still be considered by their very nature semi-structured data of the type needed to construct a model. The constrained, formulaic syntax of dictionaries and commentaries &mdash; an unnatural language designed to be quickly parsed by a human reader &mdash; lends itself equally well to parsing by relatively simple algorithms. For historical languages, secondary sources may even form a substantial part of the entire known body of the language, providing invaluable contemporary context to their literary counterparts.</p>
<p>Our project continues the practice of reading classical texts as data, but with a different aim than previous iterations of this practice: our goal is to produce a machine-learning algorithm. Some of the outlined steps that we have used to parse the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> are still works in progress, and additionally, some of the most difficult work remains to be approached. Constructing a statistical model that can represent all the complexities of current hypotheses regarding Old Chinese syllables will strain the limits of contemporary NLP platforms, most of which have no concept whatsoever of phonology. Our aim here is to persuade our peers that this task, and others like it in other languages, is not just possible but wholly worthwhile for researchers in the humanities. For this reason, we believe that further collaboration &mdash; with digital humanists, philologists, and others interested in expanding the debates around ancient texts to incorporate sound &mdash; is one of the most generative approaches to making use of NLP frameworks in the study of ancient texts.</p>
<h2 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h2>
<p>This work was made possible through our participation in the “<a href="https://newnlp.princeton.edu/">New Languages for NLP: Building Linguistic Diversity in the Digital Humanities</a>,” a National Endowment for Humanities Institute for Advanced Topics in the Digital Humanities. Our thanks to the organizers, Natalia Ermolaev and Andrew Janco, and to Toma Tasovac, Quinn Dombrowski, and David Lassner. We also thank Gissoo Doroudian and Rebecca Sutton Koeser for their design and implementation of the figures of this article, in a lively exchange with Nick Budak. Figure 4 was further based on the work of Jeffrey R. Tharsen, whose work more generally has inspired many of the thoughts in this article. Lastly, thank you to Grant Wythoff for his erudite editorial work.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Compare, however, the danger of this tendency, as shown by Emily M. Bender et al., &ldquo;On the Dangers of Stochastic Parrots: Can Language Models Be Too Big? 🦜,&rdquo; <em>FAccT &lsquo;21: Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency</em> (New York: Association for Computing Machinery, 2021), 610&ndash;23, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3442188.3445922">https://doi.org/10.1145/3442188.3445922</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This phrase is referring to the idea that in order to get a sense of the meaning of a target word, one need only carefully to select from among its surrounding context words; it draws from the title of Ashish Vaswani et al., &ldquo;Attention Is All You Need,&rdquo; <em>NIPS'17: Proceedings of the 31st International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems</em> (Red Hook: Curran Associates, 2017): 6000&ndash;10, <a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/file/3f5ee243547dee91fbd053c1c4a845aa-Paper.pdf">https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/file/3f5ee243547dee91fbd053c1c4a845aa-Paper.pdf</a>.  &ldquo;Attention&rdquo; refers specifically to an algorithmic method of calculating the importance of context words relative to the target.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Because large language models are, in effect, collections of billions or even <em>trillions</em> of individual weights or parameters, this term is used to refer to the meta-values that are used to configure and train the model itself.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Compare, in this context, insights from Toma Tasovac et al., &ldquo;Humanistic NLP: Bridging the Gap Between Digital Humanities and Natural Language Processing&rdquo; (paper, Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations Conference, Graz, Austria, July 13, 2023).&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Nick Budak and Gian Duri Rominger, &ldquo;DIRECT: Digital Intertextual Resonances in Early Chinese Texts,&rdquo; GitHub, last modified August 17, 2023, <a href="https://github.com/direct-phonology">https://github.com/direct-phonology</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Besides manuscripts stemming from archaeologically excavated sites, numerous looted manuscripts have surfaced in the last few decades. For issues regarding this trend, compare Paul R. Goldin, &ldquo;<em>Heng Xian</em> and the Problems of Studying Looted Artifacts,&rdquo; <em>Dao</em> 12 (2013): 153&ndash;60, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11712-013-9323-4">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11712-013-9323-4</a>; compare also Goldin&rsquo;s response to his critics in &ldquo;The Problem of Looted Artifacts in Chinese Studies: A Rejoinder to Critics,&rdquo; <em>Dao</em> 22 (2023): 145&ndash;51, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11712-022-09870-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11712-022-09870-8</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>Compare, for example, &ldquo;SuPar-Kanbun,&rdquo; a BERT model trained on Classical texts; see Koichi Yasuoka et al, &ldquo;Designing Universal Dependencies for Classical Chinese and Its Application.&rdquo; <em>Journal of Information Processing Society of Japan</em> 63, no. 2 (2022): 355&ndash;63, <a href="http://id.nii.ac.jp/1001/00216242/">http://id.nii.ac.jp/1001/00216242/</a>. In such models, the target language is often simply defined in opposition to modern Standard Chinese, and the training data consists of texts from across the millennia.&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:8">
<p>Pronunciation data, often rendered in the International Phonetic Alphabet, is at best noise and at worst misinformation for Transformer models; the significance of a newspaper headline like the <em>Washington Post</em>&rsquo;s description of Starbucks CEO Howard Schultz&rsquo;s 2020 campaign as being in &ldquo;a whole latte trouble&rdquo; would be completely lost. See Dana Milbank, &ldquo;Howard Schultz Brings a Whole Latte Trouble,&rdquo; <em>Washington Post</em>, January 30, 2019, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/howard-schultz-brings-a-whole-latte-trouble/2019/01/30/6d45a1ee-24cb-11e9-ad53-824486280311_story.html">https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/howard-schultz-brings-a-whole-latte-trouble/2019/01/30/6d45a1ee-24cb-11e9-ad53-824486280311_story.html</a>. For an overview of the so-called Masters literature (<em>zi shu</em>) and issues within this genre, compare, for example, Wiebke Denecke, <em>The Dynamics of Masters Literature: Early Chinese Thought From Confucius to Han Feizi</em> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2010). For the importance of sound in texts, compare, for example, Wolfgang Behr, &ldquo;Three Sound-Correlated Text Structuring Devices in Pre-Qín Philosophical Prose,&rdquo; <em>Bochumer Jahrbuch zur Ostasienforschung</em> 29 (2005): 15&ndash;33, <a href="https://zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/113766/">https://zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/113766/</a>. For discussions of the transformative effects of sounds, music, and poetry, see Haun Saussy, <em>The Problem of a Chinese Aesthetic</em> (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1993), 77&ndash;105; and Steven Van Zoeren, <em>Poetry and Personality. Reading, Exegesis, and Hermeneutics in Traditional China</em> (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1991), 95&ndash;103. On the relationship between music and rulership in early China and its assumed cultivating effects, see especially Kenneth J. DeWoskin, <em>A Song for One or Two. Music and the Concept of Art in Early China</em> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, Center for Chinese Studies; Michigan Papers in Chinese Studies no. 42, 1982), 13&ndash;14, 85&ndash;98.&#160;<a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:9">
<p>Compare, for example, Martin Kern, &ldquo;Creating a Book and Performing It: The &lsquo;Yao lüe&rsquo; Chapter of the <em>Huainanzi</em> as a Western Han <em>Fu</em>,&rdquo; in <em>The</em> Huainanzi <em>and Textual Production in Early China</em>, ed. Sarah A. Queen and Michael Puett (Leiden: Brill, 2014), 124&ndash;50.&#160;<a href="#fnref:9" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:10">
<p>See Frederick Liu, Han Lu, and Graham Neubig, &ldquo;Handling Homographs in Neural Machine Translation,&rdquo; in <em>Proceedings of the 2018 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language Technologies,</em> vol. 1 (New Orleans: Association for Computational Linguistics, 2018), 1336&ndash;45, <a href="https://aclanthology.org/N18-1121">https://aclanthology.org/N18-1121</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:10" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:11">
<p>Compare, for example, Martin Kern, &ldquo;The <em>Odes</em> in Excavated Manuscripts,&rdquo; in <em>Text and Ritual in Early China</em> (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 2005), 149&ndash;193, esp. 171. For broader overviews of the developments of Chinese writing in antiquity, compare Xigui Qiu, Gilbert Louis Mattos, and Jerry Norman, <em>Chinese Writing</em> (Berkeley: Society for the Study of Early China, 2000); William G. Boltz, <em>The Origin and the Development of the Chinese Writing System</em> (New Haven: American Oriental Society, 2003); and Imre Galambos, <em>Orthography of Early Chinese Writing: Evidence from Newly Excavated Manuscripts</em> (Budapest: Department of East Asian Studies, Eötvös Loránd University, 2006).&#160;<a href="#fnref:11" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:12">
<p>Compare David Schaberg, &ldquo;Speaking of Documents: <em>Shu</em> Citations in Warring States Texts,&rdquo; in <em>Origins of Chinese Political Philosophy</em>, ed. Martin Kern and Dirk Meyer (Leiden: Brill, 2017), 320&ndash;59. Compare also recent arguments regarding the applicability of the concept of <em>mouvance</em> to early Chinese textual phenomena; see Martin Kern, &ldquo;&lsquo;Xi Shuai&rsquo; 蟋蟀 (&lsquo;Cricket&rsquo;) and Its Consequences: Issues in Early Chinese Poetry and Textual Studies,&rdquo; <em>Early China</em> 42 (2019): 39&ndash;74, esp. 56&ndash;62, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/eac.2019.1">https://doi.org/10.1017/eac.2019.1</a>; compare also Dirk Meyer, <em>Documentation and Argument in Early China: The</em> Shangshu <em>(Venerated Documents) and the</em> Shu <em>Traditions</em> (Berlin: De Gruyter, 2021), 17&ndash;19.&#160;<a href="#fnref:12" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:13">
<p>For the underlying logic of representing early Chinese texts through visualizations of their phonological features, and for a fuller aural representation of the poem  “Guan ju” upon which figure 4 is largely based, see Jeffrey R. Tharsen, “From Form to Sound 自形至聲: Visual and Aural Representations of Premodern Chinese Phonology and Phonorhetoric with Applications for Phonetic Scripts.” <em>International Journal of Digit Humanities</em> 4 (2023), 115–129, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-022-00053-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-022-00053-8</a>. Further note that the Ming dynasty scholar Chen Di 陳第 (1541–1617) used this problem of the Odes not rhyming to persuasively make the case that the Chinese language had undergone significant phonological change since ancient times; see William H. Baxter, <em>A Handbook of Old Chinese Phonology</em> (Berlin: Mouton De Gruyter, 1992), 154–55.&#160;<a href="#fnref:13" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:14">
<p>For more background on different premodern Chinese lexicons, compare Zev Handel, &ldquo;Early Lexicons,&rdquo; in <em>Literary Information in China: A History</em>, ed. Jack W. Chen et al., (New York: Columbia University Press, 2021), 53&ndash;64, esp. 60&ndash;61 for the <em>Qieyun</em> and sound-based lexicons; and also Victor H. Mair, &ldquo;<em>Tzu-shu</em> 字書 or <em>tzu-tien</em> 字典 [Dictionaries],&rdquo; in <em>The Indiana Companion to Traditional Chinese Literature</em>, ed. William H. Nienhauser, vol. 2 (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1998); for more on the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>, see David B. Honey, <em>Northern and Southern Dynasties, Sui, and Early Tang: The Decline of Factual Philology and the Rise of Speculative Hermeneutics</em>, vol. 3 of <em>A History of Classical Chinese Scholarship</em> (Washington: Academica Press, 2021), 215&ndash;20.&#160;<a href="#fnref:14" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:15">
<p>See David B. Honey&rsquo;s translation of Lu Deming&rsquo;s biography from the <em>New Tang History</em> (<em>Xin Tang shu</em> 新唐書) in <em>Decline of Factual Philology</em>, 216&ndash;19.&#160;<a href="#fnref:15" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:16">
<p>The use of the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> as a data source was pioneered by Jeffrey R. Tharsen and Hantao Wang, who categorized and segmented the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> systematically as a database; see Jeffrey R. Tharsen and Hantao Wang, “Digitizing the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em>《經典釋文》: Deriving a Lexical Database from Ancient Glosses” (poster,  Chicago Colloquium on Digital Humanities and Computer Science (DHCS), University of Chicago, USA, November 14, 2015. <a href="https://doi.org/10.6082/uchicago.8367">https://doi.org/10.6082/uchicago.8367</a>); see also Jeffrey R. Tharsen, “Understanding the Databases of Premodern China: Harnessing the Potential of Textual Corpora as Digital Data Sources” (paper, Digital Research in East Asian Studies: Corpora, Methods, and Challenges Conference, Leiden University, the Netherlands, July 12, 2016. <a href="https://doi.org/10.6082/uchicago.8368">https://doi.org/10.6082/uchicago.8368</a>). We were initially unaware of the work of Tharsen and Wang, and at first approached the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> purely from the needs of training a Natural Language Processing model. Our approach therefore utilizes a different labeling schema that was focused on the NLP model training, and a different digitized version of the source text. Nonetheless, we are grateful for Tharsen and Wang for generously sharing their data, which allowed us to compare their data and approach to ours. As part of our approach, we understand the <em>Jingdian Shiwen</em> as a dictionary, and we identify its semi-structured dictionary form also as the reason why an approach relying solely on the Transformer architecture would be misleading. Compare this to the ability of a human reader who speaks English to look up any word she may find in a source text in the <em>Oxford English Dictionary</em>. GPT-3 processes the same text differently, and the only way it learns from the dictionary as a text is in the same way it understands a sequential text like <em>Moby-Dick</em>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:16" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:17">
<p>For comparison, in terms of file size, the modern &ldquo;gzip&rdquo; algorithm compresses the entirety of the same corpus with a ratio of about 3:1.&#160;<a href="#fnref:17" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:18">
<p>This more abstract understanding of phonology may have reached Chinese scholars by way of Sanskrit and Indian linguistics, which had gained relevance with the increasing institutionalization of Chinese Buddhism in the sixth and seventh centuries; compare Mair, “<em>Tzu-shu</em> 字書,” 168.&#160;<a href="#fnref:18" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:19">
<p>&ldquo;About Kanseki Repository,&rdquo; Kanripo, last accessed August 21, 2023, <a href="https://www.kanripo.org/">https://www.kanripo.org/</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:19" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:20">
<p>Nick Budak and Gian Duri Rominger, &ldquo;DIRECT: Digital Intertextual Resonances in Early Chinese Texts,&rdquo; GitHub, last modified August 17, 2023, <a href="https://github.com/direct-phonology">https://github.com/direct-phonology</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:20" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:21">
<p>For the Prodigy annotation tool, see &ldquo;Prodigy 101 &mdash; Everything You Need to Know,&rdquo; Prodigy, accessed August 12, 2023, <a href="https://prodi.gy/docs">https://prodi.gy/docs</a>. For spaCy, see &ldquo;spaCy 101: Everything You Need to Know,&rdquo; spaCy, accessed August 21, 2023, <a href="https://spacy.io/usage/spacy-101">https://spacy.io/usage/spacy-101</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:21" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:22">
<p>For this reconstruction, see William H. Baxter and Laurent Sagart, <em>Old Chinese: A New Reconstruction</em> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199945375.001.0001">https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199945375.001.0001</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:22" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:23">
<p>For an example of this technique as applied to finding quoted passages in Chinese text, compare Paul Vierthaler and Mees Gelein, &ldquo;A BLAST-Based, Language-Agnostic Text Reuse Algorithm with a MARKUS Implementation and Sequence Alignment Optimized for Large Chinese Corpora,&rdquo; <em>Journal of Cultural Analytics</em> 4, no. 2 (2019), <a href="https://doi.org/10.22148/16.034">https://doi.org/10.22148/16.034</a>; this inspired <a href="https://github.com/direct-phonology/dphon">our dphon tool</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:23" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">On the Institutional Landscape in East Asian Studies DH</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/institutional-landscape/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/institutional-landscape/</id><author><name>Anna M. Shields</name></author><published>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T15:48:34-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In March of 2023, Harvard University hosted &ldquo;<a href="https://sites.harvard.edu/tools-of-the-trade/">Tools of the Trade: The Way Forward</a>,&rdquo; an exciting three-day conference surveying recent trends in East Asian digital humanities (DH). With the support of a wide range of <a href="https://sites.harvard.edu/tools-of-the-trade/sponsors/">funding sources from Harvard and abroad</a>, over 150 participants attended from the United States, Europe, and East Asia. The papers and plenary sessions covered over three thousand years of East Asian history, included multiple East Asian languages and scripts, and featured new databases, platforms, and methodologies in DH research.</p>
<p>The participants represented an equally wide range of national centers and East Asian, European, and U.S. institutions; unsurprisingly, junior scholars were especially active throughout the conference. As Alíz Horváth and Hilde De Weerdt noted in their recent introduction to a special issue of the <em>International Journal of Digital Humanities</em> on East Asian DH, the rapid expansion of computational and data-driven research in East Asian studies is everywhere in evidence: in new dissertations, journals, conferences, job opportunities, and workshops.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    Now seems to be a good moment for East Asianists across institutions to strategize about sharing resources.
</blockquote>
<p>Interest among East Asianists in new tools and methods can be seen among scholars across the globe, but it is clear that East Asian nations are leading the way in terms of public funding for this new work at top universities, libraries, and national centers. The Harvard conference also, and perhaps unexpectedly, shed light on the uneven institutional landscape in North America for DH research in East Asian studies and prompted reflections on how institutions might collaborate to promote this work more effectively and systematically. In the current structure of graduate education in the U.S., many PhDs are trained in area studies departments at institutions that may or may not have DH centers like those at Princeton, <a href="https://digitalhumanities.stanford.edu/">Stanford University,</a> and the <a href="https://dh.library.virginia.edu/">University of Virginia</a>, for example. They may also have limited access to skills workshops aimed at humanists, such as those that have been sponsored at the annual meeting of the <a href="https://www.asianstudies.org/">Association for Asian Studies</a>, the field organization that has also launched <a href="https://www.asianstudies.org/grants-awards/striving-for-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-in-asian-studies-humanities-grants-for-asian-studies-scholars/aas-fellowships/#aas-digital-humanities-fellowships">new DH fellowships</a>. Senior advisors may be slow to recognize the potential of DH in East Asian studies, and many junior scholars are necessarily self-taught in the tools, methods, and software that are changing their fields.</p>
<p>National organizations like the <a href="https://www.mellon.org/search/digital%20humanities">Mellon Foundation</a> and the <a href="https://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh/resources-for-applicants-to-the-NEH-office-of-digital-humanities">National Endowment for the Humanities</a> have been generous, enthusiastic funders of DH research, including training programs at a range of smaller and medium-sized institutions; such programs are of course highly competitive and limited in number. But given the rapid growth and significance of computational research in East Asian studies, as well as some of the language- and script-specific challenges that East Asian data and corpora pose, now seems to be a good moment for East Asianists <em>across</em> institutions to strategize about sharing resources and creating new opportunities &mdash; in order to increase access for more scholars and build out East Asian humanities more broadly.</p>
<p>Many possibilities spring to mind, some of which are already underway, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>cross-institutional partnerships to sponsor online workshops (that could be archived for viewing)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>the creation of open-source textbooks aimed at teaching digital toolkits to East Asian specialists, which could be implemented in graduate training</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>collaboration among libraries with strong East Asian digital resources to share (within necessary restrictions) materials and tools.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Whether or not scholars wish to incorporate data and computational methods in their research on East Asia after having access to these opportunities, such efforts would increase awareness of the potential of those methods, work to lessen the barriers to understanding new tools, and increase DH literacy within and across national borders.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Alíz Horváth and Hilde De Weerdt, introduction to “Special Issue on Digital Humanities and East Asian Studies,” ed. Alíz Horváth and Hilde De Weerdt, <em>International Journal of Digital Humanities</em> 4, nos. 1–3 (Feb. 2023): 1–4,  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-022-00064-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-022-00064-5</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">Toward a Deep Map of Chang’an: Some Reflections of a (Beginning) Practitioner</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/toward-deep-map/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/toward-deep-map/</id><author><name>Xin Wen 文欣</name></author><published>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-04T15:48:34-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Chang&rsquo;an (modern Xi&rsquo;an, Shaanxi province) is one of the most renowned cities in Chinese history. It was the capital of the Western Han (202 BCE&ndash;8 CE) and the Tang (618&ndash;907) dynasties: the twin peaks of imperial power in premodern China. In its heyday during the Tang dynasty, the area covered by the walled city (84.1 square kilometers) was even bigger than many modern metropoles, such as the island of Manhattan (59.1 square kilometers). When you visit the modern city Xi&rsquo;an now, you can still see the remnants of the Han dynasty city of Chang&rsquo;an to the northwest of the modern city center and, much more prominently, of the Tang city of Chang&rsquo;an that overlaps with a large part of the modern city. As I witnessed firsthand walking the crowded streets of Xi&rsquo;an during the sweltering summer of 2023, there is a tremendous amount of interest in the history of Chang&rsquo;an among the general population, partly because of the remains of the ancient city, partly triggered by fictional works like the popular novel and TV drama <em>The Longest Day in Chang&rsquo;an</em>.</p>
<p>Because of Chang&rsquo;an&rsquo;s historical significance, there have been efforts to map it since the Han dynasty.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> The earliest extant maps date to 1080 in the Northern Song dynasty (960&ndash;1127), when a group of local elites created a map of the city itself and maps of the palaces.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> These maps are also the earliest city maps in Chinese history. Subsequently, maps of Chang&rsquo;an were made often as a part of a &ldquo;local gazetteer,&rdquo; a kind of geographically based compilation of local historical information.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> Such production continued into, and in many cases beyond, the Qing dynasty (1644&ndash;1911). In the twentieth century, historians and geographers began producing a kind of &ldquo;historical map&rdquo; (<em>lishi ditu</em>) that was intended to show the geographical contours of a place in a specific historical period. Chang&rsquo;an, once again, was a center of scholarly interest in the production of such maps.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    During the building of an extensive subway system in 2006, many ancient tombs, old sites, and forgotten treasure hoards were excavated and rediscovered.
</blockquote>
<p>Yet, two trends that accelerated in the late twentieth century threaten to make these thoughtfully crafted historical maps obsolete, while offering new opportunities to reconceptualize how we represent Chang&rsquo;an geographically. The first is new archaeological discoveries that have been appearing at a breathtaking pace. Because of the explosive economic development of Xi&rsquo;an in the past half century and the accompanying construction of new infrastructure &mdash; notably during the building of an extensive subway system in 2006 &mdash; many ancient tombs, old sites, and forgotten treasure hoards were excavated and rediscovered. In the span of one year from 2021 to 2022, for instance, archaeologists found over 1,200 old tombs just from the west side of the city.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> These finds substantially changed our understanding of the shape of the city. When I visited an archaeological site in the summer of 2023, I observed how archaeologists uncovered a previously unknown section of the Zhuque boulevard &mdash; the main north-south axis of the Tang city &mdash; and found five unrecorded bridges over the boulevard. Such new discoveries far outpace the revision of traditional print books and atlases and cannot be properly and promptly reflected in these works.</p>
<p>At the same time, the development of GIS (Geographic Information System) technology, the use of portable GPS devises, app-based location services, and new developments in the field of digital humanities also made it possible to imagine a new kind of &ldquo;deep map&rdquo; that can incorporate and consolidate a huge amount of data, and to visualize them in ways that are easy to digest and manipulate. This deep map ideally will incorporate all the existing historical data about Chang&rsquo;an, store and organize those textual, visual, and archaeological data in accessible and sensible ways, and visualize them in various forms for open-access use. This essay reflects some of my initial thinking as I begin to conceptualize this project, one that is certainly beyond the capacity of one person. To do so, I first examine existing maps of Chang&rsquo;an produced by premodern cartographers and modern scholars, and discuss their uses and limits. Then I assess the nature of the data now at our disposal that are the basis of a &ldquo;deep map&rdquo; of Chang&rsquo;an, and envision what kind of things this new map can do for us, as researchers, students, and even tourists of modern Xi&rsquo;an.</p>
<h2 id="existing-historical-maps">Existing Historical Maps</h2>
<p>To make new maps, we need to understand what &ldquo;old&rdquo; maps look like. Although maps were continuously made about Chang&rsquo;an from the Han to the Tang dynasties, the earliest preserved map of Chang&rsquo;an dates, as mentioned earlier, to the eleventh and twelfth century in the Northern Song dynasty (960&ndash;1127). Along with the map itself, a colophon was carved on a stone and preserved in later written sources, that allows us to understand the cartographic thinking of its creators. According to the colophon, the &ldquo;principle&rdquo; (<em>fa</em> 法) for the production of this map is as follows:<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup></p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Sui capital city (which later became the Tang capital city) itself and the Daming Palace (a Tang palace located to the northeast of the capital city) are both converted on the scale of one <em>li</em> (about 460 meters) to two <em>cun</em> (each <em>cun</em> is about three centimeters). For [areas] outside of the city that are incorporated into the map, such principle of conversion does not apply. [This map] is largely based on old maps and the <span style="font-style: normal;">Record of the Western Capital</span> by Wei Shu; we also consulted many other books and investigated traces of old sites. This conversion method does not allow us to show the many halls . . . within the three Palaces, the Taiji, the Daming, and the Xingqing, so we made additional maps [for these three Palaces].</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The colophon then continues to record the sizes of the Han dynasty Chang&rsquo;an, which was included in the map, and of the Tang city, along with the number of wards in the city, the lengths and heights of walls, and the names of city gates. From this colophon, we learn two lessons about the principle of making this map of Chang&rsquo;an.</p>

<blockquote class="pull right">
    This early map of Chang&rsquo;an was created on the basis of textual evidence, earlier maps, ground surveys, and possibly even archaeological data.
</blockquote>
<p>First, the eleventh-century cartographers made use of a wide range of data, including old maps (presumably those made in the Tang dynasty), textual records of Chang&rsquo;an (especially the <em>Record of the Western Capital</em> composed by a Tang author Wei Shu in 722),<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> and personal investigations of extant sites. The leader of this project Lü Dafang (1027&ndash;1097) was from a local Chang&rsquo;an family, and served as the governor of the Chang&rsquo;an region when the map was made. His brother Lü Dalin (1044&ndash;1091), a famous antique collector, also participated in making corrections to drafts of the map. Therefore, Lü Dafang and his team must have been intimately familiar with the area and many of the ancient sites that were still visible.<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> Given that the Lü family members have been engaged in archaeological investigations in the past, it is possible that the two brothers also excavated old sites in their making of the map of Chang&rsquo;an.<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup> Therefore, this early map of Chang&rsquo;an was created on the basis of textual evidence, earlier maps, ground surveys, and possibly even archaeological data.</p>
<p>Second, the method of incorporating these data on a two-dimensional surface is also revolutionary. For the core of the map &mdash; the Sui-Tang city and the three Tang palaces &mdash; the cartographers strived to represent them accurately by following a consistent scale of conversion, about 1:7,666. Within this core, information regarding specific places is included on the basis of textual information. For instance, for the Pingkang Ward to the northeast of the city, a ward renowned among the 110 or so wards in the city for its pleasure quarters, the map includes the name of the ward itself (<em>Pingkang fang</em> 平康坊) carved in the middle of the ward; the names of important sites are placed in different areas of the ward, including Buddhist monasteries and the residences of famous officials like Chu Suiliang (596&ndash;658). These sites are represented by a simple line drawing of a small house, reflecting the influence of Chinese painting at the time.<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup> In reality, however, each of these residences and monasteries must have consisted of many individual units of houses. Beyond the city core, areas were represented primarily for inclusion rather than precision.<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> The entire southern suburb of the city, which stretched for about thirty to fifty kilometers from the southern wall of the Sui-Tang city to the Zhongnan mountains, was compressed into a narrow strip at the bottom of the map.</p>
<p>



























<figure ><img loading="lazy" alt="Close-up view of a section of a map containing a few houses and the roads between them." src="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/pingkang-ward-map.png"
     sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 80vw"
     srcset="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/pingkang-ward-map_hu06e2808c4845f15e8d4a9b0df227ac24_890162_500x0_resize_box_3.png 500w,
    /issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/pingkang-ward-map_hu06e2808c4845f15e8d4a9b0df227ac24_890162_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/pingkang-ward-map.png 972w" 
     class="landscape"
     style="max-width:450px;"><figcaption>
        <p><strong>Figure 1.</strong> Pingkang Ward according to the Chang&rsquo;an tu.<span class="attribution">Peking University Rubbing of the Map published in Tang Yanjiu, vol. 21 (2015), plate 2.13.</span>
        </p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE.  Close-up view of a section of a map containing a few houses and the roads between them.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 1.</strong> Pingkang Ward according to the Chang&rsquo;an tu.&quot;
| ATTRIBUTION: Peking University Rubbing of the Map published in Tang Yanjiu, vol. 21 (2015), plate 2.13.
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>From this brief introduction, we can see that, although remarkably accurate in its representation of the basic structures of the city (the walls, palaces, wards, and locations of gates), this unprecedented accomplishment in the early history of Chinese cartography nevertheless falls short in capturing the full richness of the city of Chang&rsquo;an in a number of ways. Due to spatial limitations, the cartographers can only include a number of the most important sites, and in a much simplified way. This one map also cannot represent the changes that occurred within the space of the city, but rather combines parts of the city the developed from different times and places them on the same map. For instance, the Daming Palace was not part of the city&rsquo;s original plan but was instead built several decades into the Tang dynasty. In this way, the map is not an accurate reflection of the city at any specific time, but an atemporal picture. Finally, because of the need to produce a map that is largely square for easy viewing and reproduction, the cartographers had to sacrifice accuracy for areas outside of the city, and squeeze in as best they could places they deemed important. The result was a rather distorted picture of the areas around Chang&rsquo;an.</p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    Lü&rsquo;s eleventh-century map remained <span style="font-style: normal;">the</span> standard Chang&rsquo;an map until the late twentieth century.
</blockquote>
<p>These issues with the otherwise revolutionary map would not be addressed, or perhaps even recognized, for centuries. The maps of Chang&rsquo;an produced after Lü Dazhong&rsquo;s map in the Southern Song through the Qing dynasties, though interesting in their own ways, were as a rule even less accurate and less rich than the Northern Song map.<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup> Therefore, Lü&rsquo;s eleventh-century map remained <em>the</em> standard Chang&rsquo;an map until the late twentieth century, when scholars began using newer technology to produce new kinds of maps of Chang&rsquo;an. The culmination of such &ldquo;modern&rdquo; scholarship is the <em>Historical Atlas of Xi&rsquo;an</em> (<em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>) published by the historical geographer Shi Nianhai in 1996.<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup> Shi&rsquo;s atlas contains eighty-nine maps of the Xi&rsquo;an region from Neolithic times down to the late twentieth century. It is arranged chronologically, with an emphasis on the Han and Tang dynasties. In particular, there are twenty maps of the Sui-Tang city, which account for almost a quarter of the whole atlas.</p>
<p>In important ways, this atlas followed the practice of Lü Dazhong&rsquo;s map. It included maps of the Sui-Tang city itself, but also maps of the three Tang palaces.<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup> But it also addressed the issues of Lü Dazhong&rsquo;s map in several ways. For the city itself, the 1996 atlas included several kinds of maps, such as a map of residential units, one on commercial establishments, one on religious institutions, and one on gardens, wells, canals, and springs.<sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup> In this way, it contained a significantly richer array of information than the eleventh-century map. By presenting three maps (Sui dynasty Chang&rsquo;an, early Tang Chang&rsquo;an before 755, and late Tang Chang&rsquo;an after 756), the atlas tries to capture the historical changes of the urban space in the three centuries of the Sui-Tang empire.<sup id="fnref:16"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup> Finally, instead of squeezing the suburban areas into the margins of the main maps, the atlas uses separate maps to represent the southern suburb, an area of villas and monasteries, and the northern suburb, where one finds all the Tang imperial mausoleums. These maps do not use distorted proportions, and are thus more accurate representations of the city and its relation to its environs.<sup id="fnref:17"><a href="#fn:17" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup></p>
<p>The most notable innovation of this atlas compared to traditional maps is its treatment of archaeological materials. In addition to maps and their accompanying, brief textual explanations, this atlas includes many photographs of archaeological sites &mdash; places of importance that were still visible to visitors &mdash; and archaeological finds. We find images of the ruins of the Han city,<sup id="fnref:18"><a href="#fn:18" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup> as well as treasures found in the Tang city and the surrounding Tang tombs.<sup id="fnref:19"><a href="#fn:19" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup> Uniquely, for the map of the Daming Palace, a site that has been thoroughly excavated, Shi Nianhai and his team include two maps: one based on textual information and the other on archaeological data.<sup id="fnref:20"><a href="#fn:20" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup> While they conform to each other to a large extent, the archaeological map includes more concrete shapes of buildings and the textual map contains many more names of places. The mapmakers indicate, subtly perhaps, that the job of future scholars is to further correlate these two groups of sources, both deemed important to the reconstruction of the city of Chang&rsquo;an.</p>

<blockquote class="pull right">
    The Song cartographers&rsquo; treatment of the relation between these two cities reveals a more intimate, and less rigid, understanding of the geographical dimensions of historical change.
</blockquote>
<p>In certain ways, one may argue that the Song dynasty map remains superior in recreating the city to the much more voluminous and accurate 1996 atlas. The Song map&rsquo;s attempt at drawing out the shape of the buildings and gates was largely abandoned in the atlas, where most monasteries were represented by a black dot and residences by a small square. This latter approach might be more cautious, but it also renders the image of the map dull and introduces inaccuracies in its own way. (The Buddhist monasteries were of course not just <em>dots</em>.) More importantly, the Song map includes the Han city to the northwest as an integral part of the Tang city, while the 1996 atlas separates the Han and the Tang cities, representing them in different sections of book. But in the Tang dynasty, the Han city was still prominently visible and frequently visited by Tang emperors. So the Song cartographers&rsquo; treatment of the relation between these two cities reveals a more intimate, and less rigid, understanding of the geographical dimensions of historical change.</p>
<p>There are other efforts to improve upon both the Song and the Shi Nianhai maps. In particular, the works by Heng Chye Kiang and Seo Tatsuhiko contributed significantly to the ways we reimagine Chang&rsquo;an. Heng published a digital reconstruction of the city that, for the first time in history, transformed our view of the city into a 3D one, thus revealing the scale of the city in ways that are impossible for traditional maps.<sup id="fnref:21"><a href="#fn:21" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup> Seo, on the other hand, followed a traditional format but, by using color coding, thematic arrangements, and geographical correlation &mdash; one of his maps connects the places of residence and places of burial for residents of Chang&rsquo;an &mdash; produced the most aesthetically pleasing and scholarly useful maps to date.<sup id="fnref:22"><a href="#fn:22" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup> Their work represents the best of existing scholarship on mapping Chang&rsquo;an.</p>
<h2 id="toward-a-deep-map">Toward a Deep Map</h2>
<p>The survey in the previous sections shows that, although there is an abundance of sophisticated scholarship on mapping historical Chang&rsquo;an, the overwhelming majority of approaches follows a tradition of mapmaking that in some ways began with the eleventh-century Song dynasty map of Chang&rsquo;an. These maps are, although extremely useful for certain purposes, static. Once a map is made, it becomes difficult to manipulate it and incorporate new data. On the other hand, unlike these traditional printed maps, &ldquo;deep maps,&rdquo; in the words of David J. Bodenhamer, are:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>fluid cartographic representations that reveal the complex, contingent, and dynamic context of events within and across time and space. They express the results of research but the answers they provide are not final and the map itself is always open to revision. <sup id="fnref:23"><a href="#fn:23" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>To achieve such a <em>fluid</em> cartographic representation, &ldquo;within and across time and space,&rdquo; one needs to build a geotemporal database that can be queried, visualized, and regularly updated. The raw materials for such a database include primarily textual sources and archaeological data. To explain how I envision building this database, I will briefly examine the nature of these two kinds of data.</p>
<p>There is a long tradition of writing about the city in China, and the writing about Chang&rsquo;an is at the heart of this tradition. The <em>Sanfu huangtu</em>, a work of uncertain date that contained information about early Chang&rsquo;an but was likely compiled much later, offers a textual dissection of the city, listing the palaces, gardens, gates, and streets of the city in the Western Zhou and the Han dynasties.<sup id="fnref:24"><a href="#fn:24" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup> Under each heading, the book provides a short description of the place, including its location, its history, and famous anecdotes associated with it. This kind of thematic treatment is inherited by later geographies, such as the <em>Leibian Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> produced in the Yuan dynasty (1271&ndash;1368).<sup id="fnref:25"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">25</a></sup></p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    There is a long tradition of writing about the city in China, and the writing about Chang&rsquo;an is at the heart of this tradition.
</blockquote>
<p>Another related kind of local writing began with the Song dynasty <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em>, produced by Song Minqiu (1019&ndash;1079) in 1076.<sup id="fnref:26"><a href="#fn:26" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">26</a></sup> Song&rsquo;s work includes a historical survey of the Chang&rsquo;an area, including a summary of government institutions, palaces, and cities in the Zhou, the Qin, and the Han dynasties, as well as the city in the Tang dynasty and counties around Chang&rsquo;an. This work is organized according to two different principles. First, the editor separates the materials between the city and the counties around it. Then, on the city, the book follows a chronological order, focusing on the Han and the Tang dynasty. Within the chapters on the city, it then includes textual information about the locations and history of notable sites. For example, the entry on the Pingkang Ward in the Tang city (represented above in the map excerpt, Figure 1) includes detailed information about several notable structures within the ward. An edition of the book printed in 1468 uses large characters to describe the name and location of these structures, while the smaller, double-line notes explain their history and incorporate stories about these places.</p>
<p>



























<figure ><img loading="lazy" alt="Facsimile of a manuscript page showing several lines of Chinese characters." src="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/gazetter-pingkang-ward.png"
     sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 80vw"
     srcset="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/gazetter-pingkang-ward_huddc071bdff978a0464dbb572ba606ed2_742075_500x0_resize_box_3.png 500w,
    /issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/gazetter-pingkang-ward_huddc071bdff978a0464dbb572ba606ed2_742075_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/gazetter-pingkang-ward.png 792w" 
     class="portrait"
     style=""><figcaption>
        <p><strong>Figure 2.</strong> Pingkang Ward according to the Chang&rsquo;an zhi (1076).<span class="attribution">Ming dynasty edition of Chang&rsquo;an zhi printed by Heyang Shutang in 1468.</span>
        </p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE.  Facsimile of a manuscript page showing several lines of Chinese characters.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 2.</strong> Pingkang Ward according to the Chang&rsquo;an zhi (1076).
| ATTRIBUTION: Ming dynasty edition of Chang&rsquo;an zhi printed by Heyang Shutang in 1468.
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>Therefore, unlike the thematically organized works mentioned above, the <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> provides more concrete temporal and geographical information that can be associated with the texts it includes. For instance, we can &ldquo;locate&rdquo; the chunk of text about the residence of a notable historical figure geographically in a ward in the city, and temporally in the lifetime of this figure, which is often known or deducible from other sources. Because the <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> provides the most complete list of Han and Tang place names in Chang&rsquo;an and gives their location in a relatively concrete and reliable manner, it has long been the basis for the reconstruction of Chang&rsquo;an in modern scholarship.<sup id="fnref:27"><a href="#fn:27" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">27</a></sup> I also use the <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> as a basis for my reconstruction of the city (Figure 2).</p>
<div class="interlude" id="fig4">
<table class="side-scroll" > <caption><b>Figure 3.</b> Excerpts from my transcription of the Chang’an zhi’s tabular data from 1076 CE, which listed the wards, places, and notable structures and stories of Chang’an.</caption>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>ID</th>
<th>Data Type</th>
<th>Name_Ch</th>
<th>Location</th>
<th>Time</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>Sub-Type</th>
<th>Start Date</th>
<th>End Date</th>
<th>CAZ</th>
<th>CAZ-Len</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1001002</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>開化坊</td>
<td>朱雀街東第一街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>半巳南大薦福寺寺院半以東隋煬帝在藩舊宅武德中賜尚書左僕射蕭瑀西為園後瑀子鋭尚㐮城公主詔别營主第主辭以姑婦異居有乖禮則因固請乃取園地充主第又辭公主棨㦸不欲異門乃併施瑀之院門㐮城薨後官市為英王宅文明元年髙宗崩後百日立為大獻福寺度僧二百人以實之天授元年改為薦福寺中宗即位大加營飾自神龍以後翻譯佛經並於此寺寺東院有放生池周二百餘歩傳云即漢代洪池陂也西門之北法壽尼寺隋開皇六年立國子祭酒韓洄宅尚書左僕射令狐楚宅按酉陽雜爼楚宅在開化坊牡丹最盛而李商隱詩多言晉陽里第未詳户部尚書馬揔宅河東節度使兼侍中李光顔宅穆宗初賜第崇徳坊以為别宅尚書吏部侍郎沈傅師宅前司徒兼侍中崔垂休宅漕渠㑹要京兆尹韓朝宗分渭水入自金光門置潭於西市西街以貯材木又永泰二年京兆尹黎幹以京城薪炭不給鑿渠自京兆府直東至薦福寺東街北至國子監正東至子城東街並逾景風延喜門入苑</td>
<td>360</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001039</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>東市</td>
<td>朱雀街東第四街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Market</td>
<td>Market</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>隋曰都㑹市南北居二坊之地東西南北各六百歩四靣各開二門定四靣街各廣百歩北街當皇城南之大街東出春明門廣狹不易於舊東西及南靣三街向内開北廣於舊街市内貨財二百二十行四靣立邸四方珍竒皆所積集萬年縣户口减於長安又公卿以下居止多在朱雀街東第宅所占甚多由是商賈所凑多歸西市西市户口少列律寛自此之外繁雜稍劣於西市矣當中東市局次東平准局並𨽻太府寺東北隅有放生池分滻水渠自道政坊東入城西流注此池俗號為海池</td>
<td>192</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001044</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>修政坊</td>
<td>朱雀街東第四街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>尚書右丞相張九齡宅尚書省亭子宗正寺亭子輦下嵗時記曰新進士牡丹宴或在于此</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001047</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>十王宅</td>
<td>朱雀街東第五街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>盡坊之地築八苑十王宅政要先天之後皇子㓜則居内東封後以年漸近長乃於安國寺東附苑城同為大宅分院居之名為十王宅令中官押之於夾城中起居每日家令進膳十王謂慶忠棣鄂榮光儀潁永濟也其後盛壽陳豐恒涼六王又就封入内宅天寳中唯十四王居内而府幕列於外坊嵗時通名起居而内外諸孫成長又於十宅外置字孫院十五宫人每院四百餘人百孫院三四百人又於宫中置維城庫諸王月俸物納之給用諸孫婚嫁亦就十宫中太子不居東宫但居於乘輿所幸别院太子之子亦分院而居婚嫁則同親王公主於崇仁坊之禮㑹院</td>
<td>221</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001063</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>光行坊</td>
<td>朱雀街西第一街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>行字本犯中宗諱長安中改一作光仁東南隅華州刺史宇文經野宅觀軍容使魚朝恩宅</td>
<td>35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001078</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>延壽坊</td>
<td>朱雀街西第三街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>隋有惠覺寺大業七年廢南門之西懿徳寺本慈門寺隋開皇六年刑部尚書萬安公李圓通所立神龍元年中宗為懿徳太子追福改名加飾焉東南隅駙馬都尉裴巽宅其地本隋齊州刺史盧貴宅髙宗末禮部尚書裴行儉居之武太后時河内王武懿宗居之土地平敞水朩清茂為京城之最成安公主宅中宗女降韋㨗寳應經坊大厯十二年淮西節度兵馬使李重倩敗汴州李靈輝請捨所居延夀里宅為佛經坊許之仍賜名寳應一切經坊</td>
<td>173</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001091</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>西市</td>
<td>朱雀街西第四街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Market</td>
<td>Market</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>隋曰利人市南北盡兩坊之地市内有西市局𨽻太府寺市内店肆如東市已制長安縣所領四萬餘户比萬年為多浮寄流寓不可勝計市西北有池長安中沙門法成所穿支分永安渠以注之以為放生池放生池平凖局獨柳刑人之所</td>
<td>93</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1001097</td>
<td>Polygon</td>
<td>歸義坊</td>
<td>朱雀街西第四街</td>
<td>Tang</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>Ward</td>
<td>581</td>
<td>904</td>
<td>全一坊隋蜀王秀宅隋文帝以京城南面濶逺無以彈壓乃使諸子並南郭參居秀死後沒官為家令寺園</td>
<td>41</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

</div>
<p>In addition to these geographical texts devoted to Chang&rsquo;an, the vast ocean of traditional Chinese historical records includes many more sources for Chang&rsquo;an: in official annals, political treatises, fictions, and poetry, among others. They are associable to different areas of the city because they often mention places in Chang&rsquo;an as the location where the stories transpired. The Pingkang Ward, for instance, was renowned as the pleasure quarter of the city, and many encounters between courtesans and young officials and students are recorded.<sup id="fnref:28"><a href="#fn:28" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">28</a></sup> Now that I have established a database of places according to <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em>, information from these other sources can then be added to each record, enriching the dataset as a whole. The result, hopefully, will be an extensive database of textual sources that are, to various degrees of preciseness, locatable in the city of Chang&rsquo;an.</p>
<p>The second kind of data we possess in abundance now comes from archaeology. Unlike textual sources, whose geographical information can often be fuzzy, archaeological data generally contain concrete geographical information. For instance, when a hoard of Tang treasures was discovered in 1970, we know <em>precisely</em> where it was discovered: a modern village called Hejiacun (Figure 4).<sup id="fnref:29"><a href="#fn:29" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">29</a></sup> Then, cross-referencing with textual sources from <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> and others, we can determine that this hoard was located in the southwestern part of the Xinghua Ward on the west side of Chang&rsquo;an.</p>
<p>



























<figure ><img loading="lazy" alt="A golden bowl with decorative patterns and animals engraved along the side." src="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village.jpg"
     sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 80vw"
     srcset="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village_hub52f1c2daa6bb4fba8cc68c2bab176d6_3466244_500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 500w,
    /issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village_hub52f1c2daa6bb4fba8cc68c2bab176d6_3466244_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village_hub52f1c2daa6bb4fba8cc68c2bab176d6_3466244_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village_hub52f1c2daa6bb4fba8cc68c2bab176d6_3466244_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village_hub52f1c2daa6bb4fba8cc68c2bab176d6_3466244_1800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/golden-bowl-hejia-village.jpg 2560w" 
     class="landscape"
     style=""><figcaption>
        <p><strong>Figure 4.</strong> A Golden Bowl from the Hejia Village Hoard. Artifacts like these allow us to link abstract textual descriptions of a place with their geographic location.<span class="attribution"><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:%E9%B8%B3%E9%B8%AF%E8%8E%B2%E7%93%A3%E7%BA%B9%E9%87%91%E7%A2%97_20091112.jpg">Wikimedia Commons.</a></span>
        </p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE.  A golden bowl with decorative patterns and animals engraved along the side.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 4.</strong> A Golden Bowl from the Hejia Village Hoard. Artifacts like these allow us to link abstract textual descriptions of a place with their geographic location.
| ATTRIBUTION: Wikimedia Commons.
| LINK: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:%E9%B8%B3%E9%B8%AF%E8%8E%B2%E7%93%A3%E7%BA%B9%E9%87%91%E7%A2%97_20091112.jpg">https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:%E9%B8%B3%E9%B8%AF%E8%8E%B2%E7%93%A3%E7%BA%B9%E9%87%91%E7%A2%97_20091112.jpg</a>
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>Thousands of similar archaeological discoveries, from tombs and building foundations to ancient wells and gates, have been made in the past few decades. Almost all of them, when documented in official reports, are placed with a precise location that can be associated with a Tang or Han dynasty place. In this way, these archaeological data can be easily connected to the textual database. Our knowledge about their precise locations means that these archaeological data more easily lend themselves to geometric abstractions than does most textual information.</p>
<p>Furthermore, archaeology does not simply provide additional data, but can help revise and refine the textual data too. The archaeological work on the city itself &mdash; its walls, gates, bridges, and palaces &mdash; gives us a more precise picture of the shape of the city than textual sources and offers details unrecorded in texts. For instance, the excavation of what used to be the Western Market &mdash; the center of foreign trade in Tang Chang&rsquo;an &mdash; revealed details about the internal structure of the market area, including the bridges and water system that must have been crucial to the function of the city (Figure 5). None of these details are recorded in textual sources. Such archaeological data complement, correct, and enrich textual data; a full picture of the city can only become possible if both types of sources are thoroughly incorporated.</p>
<p>



























<figure ><img loading="lazy" alt="The excavation of an ancient bridge in the middle of a modern city street." src="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market.jpg"
     sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 80vw"
     srcset="/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market_hu5eee12a15e2c2c689643538063737600_3010842_500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 500w,
    /issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market_hu5eee12a15e2c2c689643538063737600_3010842_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market_hu5eee12a15e2c2c689643538063737600_3010842_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market_hu5eee12a15e2c2c689643538063737600_3010842_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market_hu5eee12a15e2c2c689643538063737600_3010842_1800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1800w,/issues/4/toward-deep-map/images/stone-bridge-western-market.jpg 4032w" 
     class="landscape"
     style=""><figcaption>
        <p><strong>Figure 5.</strong> Excavation of a Stone Bridge in the Western Market of Tang Chang&rsquo;an.<span class="attribution">Photo taken by the author.</span>
        </p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only">
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
| FIGURE.  The excavation of an ancient bridge in the middle of a modern city street.
|
| CAPTION: <strong>Figure 5.</strong> Excavation of a Stone Bridge in the Western Market of Tang Chang&rsquo;an.
| ATTRIBUTION: Photo taken by the author.
#&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;
</div></p>
<p>What can we do with a database that incorporates both textual and archaeological information? And how would this &ldquo;deep map&rdquo; differ from the existing maps surveyed above? At this point, in the beginning of my project, I can only offer a few conjectural remarks.</p>
<p>As I will be using GIS software like ArcGIS or QGIS to organize and visualize my data, the first step &mdash; by no means an easy one &mdash; is to produce a time-layered map of Chang&rsquo;an, the scale of which can be easily manipulated through zooming-in and -out features. Unlike Shi Nianhai&rsquo;s atlas, it is possible to create many more layers of different time periods, considering the changing political and cultural history of the city. The juxtaposition of maps from different eras could help readers better grasp the overlapping constructions in Chang&rsquo;an across different dynasties, which formed a kind of imperial palimpsest. There will also be virtually no limit as to how much information one can include within a certain space. Going back to the Pingkang Ward example, unlike the Song dynasty map that can only include six building complexes, GIS technology allows us to put all the information contained in the <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> and other sources under the entry of the &ldquo;Pingkang Ward&rdquo; in our database. This large amount of information can then be linked to specific locations on the map, showing either the names of specific buildings or even excerpts from the historical sources on these buildings. These annotations can be placed on a modern basemap like Google Earth&rsquo;s satellite images, or a georeferenced old map like the fragments of the Song dynasty <em>Chang&rsquo;an tu</em>. The result will be a Chang&rsquo;an map of unprecedented detail.<sup id="fnref:30"><a href="#fn:30" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">30</a></sup></p>
<p>Another aspect of the urban space of Chang&rsquo;an that most existing maps fail to grasp is its three dimensionality. As scholars have shown, the vertical space of Chang&rsquo;an was a central factor in the social life of its residents.<sup id="fnref:31"><a href="#fn:31" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">31</a></sup> Yet virtually all our existing maps use a bird&rsquo;s-eye perspective, looking down on a two-dimensional city. As we have knowledge about the magnitude of Chang&rsquo;an&rsquo;s tall buildings &mdash; some of the pagodas in Buddhist monasteries rose to over one hundred meters &mdash; and the topographical features of the city &mdash; the Tang imperial palace in the north was the lowest elevational point in the city, and was about fifty to sixty meters lower than the southeastern corner of the city &mdash; it will be possible to incorporate these data into the &ldquo;deep map&rdquo; and offer a better approximation of residents&rsquo; experiences of the city in premodern times.</p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    Fictional accounts like the love story between a courtesan and an aspiring examinee also include factual geographical information that allows us to place the flow of their plots in the space of Chang&rsquo;an.
</blockquote>
<p>What makes a map &ldquo;fluid&rdquo; is its ability to illustrate not only buildings and walls, but also <em>events</em>. There is of course no doubt that many historical events played out in the city since the earliest days of its foundation. But it was not until the Tang dynasty that significant events were recorded in textual sources with (relatively) precise geotemporal information. We know, for instance, how the Xuanwu Gate incident (July 2, 626), in which Li Shimin (598&ndash;649) killed his two brothers and forced his father (the emperor) to designate him as the heir, played out, beat by beat, in different parts of the city. Neither is such knowledge limited to historical events. Fictional accounts like the love story between a courtesan and an aspiring examinee also include factual geographical information that allows us to place the flow of their plots in the space of Chang&rsquo;an.<sup id="fnref:32"><a href="#fn:32" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">32</a></sup> The social lives of certain residents and visitors, such as the Japanese Buddhist monk Ennin who visited Chang&rsquo;an in the mid-ninth century, can also be reconstructed with remarkable precision.<sup id="fnref:33"><a href="#fn:33" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">33</a></sup> I plan to create subsets of data to document the flow of these events and show them in separate layers of maps. The data thus organized can then be animated, revealing the social lives of the city in ways impossible using printed maps.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This &ldquo;deep map&rdquo; of Chang&rsquo;an will be useful for scholars and students to learn about the city and its history. The collection of a vast amount of textual and archaeological data with new ways to organize and visualize them will certainly lead to new insights into the history and culture of the city. I cannot foresee what these insights will be. In my own research, I have certainly already benefited from even <em>thinking</em> about this deep map: an article I am writing now discusses the continued presence, in Tang Chang&rsquo;an, of physical structures and ghostly beings from the Han dynasty and earlier. The idea for this project came directly from when I tried to overlay the Han city map onto the Tang city map in QGIS. I hope this deep map will be similarly useful to other scholars in their research work.</p>
<p>As Chang&rsquo;an was the capital of China in much of the early and medieval imperial period, a better understanding of the city also would lead to a more intimate knowledge about Chinese history in general. In this sense, a more dynamic and accessible deep map of Chang&rsquo;an will no doubt be of pedagogical value and should be welcome in classrooms of Chinese history and culture, both in introductory lectures and in specialized seminars. A deep map of historical Chang&rsquo;an, if combined with portable GPS devices, will give travelers an augmented experience that no print map can match. These multiple potential uses make this deep map a worthwhile endeavor, and I look forward to the collaboration with other students of China and Chang&rsquo;an in the coming years on this project.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The earliest reference to a map of Chang&rsquo;an is found in a third-century commentary by a certain Ruchun 如淳 on the Han dynasty work <em>Shiji</em>. See Sima Qian 司馬遷, <em>Shiji</em> 史記 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1982), 10.432. This reference indicates that it is highly likely a map of Chang&rsquo;an already existed in the Han dynasty.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>These maps were preserved because they were carved on stone. The stone that carried the main map of the city had long been severely damaged, so only fragments of the map of the city are still extant. For a reconstruction of this map using rubbings, see Hu Haifan 胡海帆, &ldquo;Beijing daxue tushuguan cang Lü Dafang <em>Chang&rsquo;an tu</em> canshi taben de chubu yanjiu&quot;北京大學圖書館藏呂大防《長安圖》殘石拓本的初步研究, <em>Tang yanjiu</em> 21 (2016), 1&ndash;63.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See Joseph R. Dennis, <em>Writing, Publishing, and Reading Local Gazetteers in Imperial China, 1100&ndash;1700</em> (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Asia Center, 2015).&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>The most authoritative work in this category remains Shi Nianhai 史念海, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em> 西安歷史地圖集 (Xi&rsquo;an: Xi&rsquo;an ditu chubanshe, 1996). But see also maps in Seo Tatsuhiko 妹尾達彥, <em>Chōan no toshi keikaku</em> 長安の都市計画 (Tokyo: Kōdansha, 2001).&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See the report of <em>Huaxi dushi bao</em>, <a href="https://www.wccdaily.com.cn/shtml/hxdsb/20230705/197867.shtml">https://www.wccdaily.com.cn/shtml/hxdsb/20230705/197867.shtml</a>, accessed July 30, 2023.&#160;<a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>The colophon of this map is preserved only partially through the carved map itself. But a rough transcription of it is found in the Southern Song <em>biji</em> titled <em>Yunlu manchao</em> 雲麓漫鈔 by Zhao Yanruo 趙彥若 (1033&ndash;1095). For the fragmentary version on the stone, see Li Fangyao 李芳瑤, &ldquo;<em>Chang&rsquo;an tubei</em> xinkao 長安圖碑新考,&rdquo; <em>Wenxian</em> 2012.3, 93. For the version in <em>Yunlu manchao</em>, see Yang Xiaochun 楊曉春 &ldquo;<em>Yunlu manchao zhong de yize Sui Tang Chang&rsquo;an yanjiu zhengui shiliao de jiaodian</em>,&rdquo; 雲麓漫鈔中一則隋唐長安研究珍貴史料的校點 <em>Zhongguo lishi dili luncong</em> 20, no. 3 (2005): 144&ndash;50. I combine these two versions in my reading.&#160;<a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>This work still exists in fragments. See Wei Shu 韋述*, Liangjing xinji jijiao* 兩京新記輯校 ed. Xin Deyong 辛德勇 (Xi&rsquo;an: Sanqin chubanshe, 2006).&#160;<a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:8">
<p>See my forthcoming article, &ldquo;The Song Discovery of Chang&rsquo;an,&rdquo; <em>Journal of Song Yuan Studies</em>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:9">
<p>This is known from the many antique objects, which were discovered from ancient sites many centuries before the time of the Lü family, buried in the recently discovered Lü family graveyard. See Shaanxi sheng kaogu yanjiuyuan 陝西省考古研究院 &ldquo;Shaanxi Lantian xian Wulitou Bei Song Lüshi jiazu mudi 陝西藍田縣五里頭北宋呂氏家族墓地,&rdquo; <em>Kaogu</em> 8 (2010): 46&ndash;52.&#160;<a href="#fnref:9" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:10">
<p>Indeed, the distinction between a painting and a map was often quite blurred in premodern China.&#160;<a href="#fnref:10" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:11">
<p>Yan Shaofei 嚴少飛, Wang Shusheng 王樹聲, Li Xiaolong 李小龍, &ldquo;Neizhe wairong: yizhong rouhe ziran shanshui huanjing de chengshi tuhui moshi&rdquo; 內折外容：一種糅合自然山水環境的城市圖繪模式, <em>Chengshi guihua</em> 11 (2017).&#160;<a href="#fnref:11" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:12">
<p>Some of these maps are included in the late twelfth-century work <em>Yonglu</em>. See Cheng Dachang 程大昌, <em>Yonglu</em> 雍錄 (Xi&rsquo;an: Shaanxi shifan daxue chubanshe, 1996).&#160;<a href="#fnref:12" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:13">
<p>The first edition of the book was published in 1986, but here I use the later and updated edition.&#160;<a href="#fnref:13" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:14">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 87&ndash;90.&#160;<a href="#fnref:14" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:15">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 92&ndash;98.&#160;<a href="#fnref:15" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:16">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 74&ndash;75, 80&ndash;83.&#160;<a href="#fnref:16" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:17">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 99&ndash;106.&#160;<a href="#fnref:17" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:18">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 60.&#160;<a href="#fnref:18" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:19">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 86.&#160;<a href="#fnref:19" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:20">
<p>Shi, <em>Xi&rsquo;an lishi dituji</em>, 89.&#160;<a href="#fnref:20" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:21">
<p>Heng Chye Kiang, <em>A Digital Reconstruction of Tang Chang&rsquo;an</em> (Beijing: Zhongguo Jianzhu Gongye Chubanshe, 2006).&#160;<a href="#fnref:21" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:22">
<p>His maps are scattered through his numerous publications, but notably Seo Tatsuhiko, <em>Chōan no toshi keikaku</em>, and グローバル・ヒストリ<em>Gurōbaru hisutorī</em> (Hachiōji: Chūō Daigaku Shuppanbu 2018).&#160;<a href="#fnref:22" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:23">
<p>David J. Bodenhamer, “The Varieties of Deep Maps,” in <em>Making Deep Maps: Foundations, Approaches, and Methods</em>, ed. David J. Bodenhamer, John Corrigan, and Trevor M. Harris (Abingdon: Routledge, 2022), 6&ndash;7.&#160;<a href="#fnref:23" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:24">
<p>He Qinggu 何清谷, <em>Sanfu huangtu jiaoshi</em> 三輔黃圖校釋 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 2012).&#160;<a href="#fnref:24" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:25">
<p>Luo Tianxiang 駱天驤, <em>Leibian Chang&rsquo;an zhi</em> 類編長安志 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1990).&#160;<a href="#fnref:25" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:26">
<p>Xin Deyong 辛德勇 and Lang Jie 郎潔 ed., <em>Chang&rsquo;an zhi, Chang&rsquo;an zhi tu</em> 長安志, 長安志圖 (Xi&rsquo;an: Sanqin chubanshe, 2013).&#160;<a href="#fnref:26" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:27">
<p>Such reconstruction work was started by Xu Song 徐松 (1781&ndash;1848) in the early nineteenth century. See Xu Song, <em>Tang liangjing chengfangkao</em> 唐兩京城坊考 (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1985). Li Jianchao 李建超 has systematically added new, especially archaeological, information and produced several new expanded editions of Xu&rsquo;s work. For the latest edition, see Li, <em>Zuixin zengding Tang liangjing chengfangkao</em> 最新增訂唐兩京城坊考 (Xi&rsquo;an: Sanqin chubanshe, 2019).&#160;<a href="#fnref:27" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:28">
<p>For a translation of this text, see Howard Levy, &ldquo;The Gay Quarters of Ch&rsquo;ang-an,&rdquo; <em>Orient/West</em> 7, no. 9 (1962): 93&ndash;105; 8, no. 6 (1963): 15&ndash;22; 9, no. 1 (1964): 3&ndash;10.&#160;<a href="#fnref:28" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:29">
<p>Valerie Hansen, “The Hejia Village Hoard: A Snapshot of China&rsquo;s Silk Road Trade,” <em>Orientations</em> 34, no. 2 (February 2003), 14&ndash;19.&#160;<a href="#fnref:29" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:30">
<p>In this regard, I have been inspired by the work of David Gilman Romano on Augustan Rome. David Gilman Romano, “Digital Augustan Rome,” University of Arizona, accessed September 10, 2023, <a href="https://www.digitalaugustanrome.org">https://www.digitalaugustanrome.org</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:30" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:31">
<p>Linda Rui-Feng, &ldquo;Negotiating Vertical Space: Walls, Vistas, and the Topographical Imagination.&rdquo; <em>T&rsquo;ang Studies</em> 29 (2011): 27&ndash;44, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/tan.2011.0002">https://doi.org/10.1353/tan.2011.0002</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:31" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:32">
<p>Glen Dudbridge, <em>The Tale of Li Wa, Study and Critical Edition of a Chinese Story from the Ninth Century</em> (London: Ithaca Press, 1983).&#160;<a href="#fnref:32" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:33">
<p>Seo Tatsuhiko, &ldquo;Buddhism and Commerce in Ninth-Century Chang&rsquo;an: A study of Ennin&rsquo;s Nittō Guhō Junrei Kōki 入唐求法巡禮行記,&rdquo; <em>Studies in Chinese Religions</em> 5, no. 2 (2019): 85&ndash;104.&#160;<a href="#fnref:33" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content></entry></feed>