<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue 4 on Startwords</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/</link><description>Recent content in Issue 4 on Startwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu (Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton)</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu (Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Of Sonorous Medieval Chinese Texts and NLP Model Training</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/sonorous-medieval/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Nick Budak, Gian Rominger</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/sonorous-medieval/</guid><description>A distinctive set of challenges arises when training machines to process a historical language, especially one that was last spoken two millennia ago.</description></item><item><title>On the Institutional Landscape in East Asian Studies DH</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/institutional-landscape/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Anna M. Shields</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/institutional-landscape/</guid><description>In March of 2023, Harvard University hosted &amp;ldquo;Tools of the Trade: The Way Forward,&amp;rdquo; an exciting three-day conference surveying recent trends in East Asian digital humanities (DH). With the support of a wide range of funding sources from Harvard and abroad, over 150 participants attended from the United States, Europe, and East Asia. The papers and plenary sessions covered over three thousand years of East Asian history, included multiple East Asian languages and scripts, and featured new databases, platforms, and methodologies in DH research.</description></item><item><title>Toward a Deep Map of Chang’an: Some Reflections of a (Beginning) Practitioner</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/toward-deep-map/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Xin Wen 文欣</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/4/toward-deep-map/</guid><description>Chang’an is one of the most renowned cities in Chinese history. It was the capital of the Western Han (202 BCE—8 CE) and the Tang (618—907) dynasties: the twin peaks of imperial power in premodern China.</description></item></channel></rss>