<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Issue Two on Startwords</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/</link><description>Recent content in Issue Two on Startwords</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>cdh-info@princeton.edu (Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton)</managingEditor><webMaster>cdh-info@princeton.edu (Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>“Strangers in the Landscape”: On Research Development and Making Things for Making</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/strangers-in-the-landscape/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Samantha Blickhan, Will Granger, Shaun A. Noordin, Becky Rother</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/strangers-in-the-landscape/</guid><description>This piece is about making in support of making. It is about projects born from myriad goals that gather new objectives along their lifecycle, through evaluation and iteration.</description></item><item><title>Creating and Recreating Virtual Community on Douglass Day</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/creating-and-recreating-virtual-community/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Justin Smith, Courtney Murray, Jim Casey</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/creating-and-recreating-virtual-community/</guid><description>Save the Date for Douglass Day 2022!
Help us find the names of Black women in the Colored Conventions. Where did they go?
Registration is now open. Sign up for updates &amp;amp; more! https://t.co/nbxI9l1lGT pic.twitter.com/5bz5fRQVLR
&amp;mdash; Douglass Day (@DouglassDayorg) October 8, 2021 Save the Date for Douglass Day 2022! Help us find the names of Black women in the Colored Conventions. Where did they go? Registration is now open. Sign up for updates &amp;amp; more!</description></item><item><title>Data's Destinations: Three Case Studies in Crowdsourced Transcription Data Management and Dissemination</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/datas-destinations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Victoria Anne Van Hyning, Mason A. Jones</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/datas-destinations/</guid><description>Online crowdsourcing—a series of methods for engaging volunteers with STEM, humanities, and cultural heritage research—has rapidly matured between 2000 and 2021.</description></item><item><title>Serendipity in the Cairo Geniza</title><link>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/serendipity-in-the-cairo-geniza/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Matthew Dudley, Steffy Reader</author><guid>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/2/serendipity-in-the-cairo-geniza/</guid><description>Matthew Dudley is a PhD candidate at Yale University where he is completing a dissertation on the early modern Cairo Geniza of the sixteenth through nineteenth centuries. Steffy Reader, a retired psychotherapist, has contributed to the Scribes of the Cairo Geniza and a number of other Zooniverse projects since 2018. In the clip below, they meet for the first time during the conference Crowdsourcing and the Humanities and discover that they had already been collaborating anonymously via the Scribes of the Cairo Geniza site.</description></item></channel></rss>