<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.67.1">Hugo</generator><title type="html">Issue One on Startwords</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HTML"/><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/index.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="RSS"/><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" title="Atom"/><updated>2020-10-16T16:30:06+00:00</updated><rights>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</rights><author><name>Center for Digital Humanities at Princeton</name><email>cdh-info@princeton.edu</email></author><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/</id><entry><title type="html">Data Beyond Vision</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/</id><author><name>Rebecca Sutton Koeser</name></author><author><name>Gissoo Doroudian</name></author><author><name>Nick Budak</name></author><author><name>Xinyi Li</name></author><published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T12:29:28-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do we represent tangible objects in a visual medium? We use words, pictures, and diagrams. We describe, share, show, and fail.</p>
<p>Humanists continue to expand the range of texts they study, but the range of scholarly outputs has not seen a similar expansion. While there are movements within Digital Humanities to consider formats beyond the traditional, the presentation and publishing of more innovative and experimental works (such as installations and project demos) is still secondary or sidelined, where it exists at all.  What would it look like to consider non-textual research outputs as first-order scholarly work? The historian David Staley suggests the terms  “interpretive objects” or “humanistic objects” for creative scholarly acts that are not limited to text.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Innovative work like this is carefully researched and theorized, and deserves scholarly engagement and intellectual rigor even if it does not fit into established modes of scholarly communication.</p>
<p>Academic research has a long history of textual scholarly practice and citation that we haven’t yet figured out how to adapt to non-textual scholarship. The <a href="https://openhumanitiesdata.metajnl.com/">Journal of Open Humanities Data</a> and <a href="https://joss.theoj.org/">The Journal of Open Source Software</a> can
both be seen as steps in this direction: they provide venues for the review and publication of data and software, respectively, accompanied by brief “metapapers”; but even these rely on transforming the content they review (data and software) into text in order to function! What are the implications if we truly expand the range of accepted scholarly outputs to include such interpretive objects as data structures, databases, software, datasets, physical objects, augmented reality experiences? Will all scholars need to become experts in all these modes, or can we find a way to be conversant, as with other important scholarly theories?</p>
<div class="" id="interlude">
<div class="left" id="">
<p><strong>SEE</strong></p>
<p>from a distance.<br>
Cold, commanding.<br>
Sense of mastery,<br>
but optical illusions deceive.</p>
<p>Look in a mirror.<br>
and see yourself<br>
seeing.</p>
</div>
<div class="right" id="">
<p><strong>TOUCH</strong></p>
<p>up close.<br>
Intimate, incomplete.<br>
Explore partial knowledge,<br>
enlighten slowly.</p>
<p>Run fingers across skin<br>
and touch yourself<br>
touching.</p>
</div>

</div>
<p>These are not artist statements because this is not art; Data Art is something else. This is representation, correspondence, laborious translation. Call them maker statements, perhaps. These are our attempts to communicate our goals and help you read and interpret these unfamiliar objects and be challenged by the potential of physicalizations.</p>
<p>Data physicalization focuses on constructing data in physical form. It may be similar to other approaches in that it helps to understand and represent data, and in its use of the senses to communicate information, mainly through touch and sight. However, there are considerable distinctions among these approaches. What makes data physicalization distinct is that it encourages critical making by bridging the gap between creative physical and conceptual exploration. This matters because not only does it surfaces the amount of labor involved with data production and representation, and put it into different perspectives and dimensions; it can also creates an opportunity for viewers to become participants by taking part in the making of a piece using data.</p>
<p>Data Physicalization attempts to defamiliarize our eyes from many of the two-dimensional data representations we have seen, and put us “in the middle of data”. There is something unique about turning data points into physical forms and placing them in space that triggers the mind to understand data in a distinctive way.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<p>










 


<figure>
    
    <img src="/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/conceptmap.svg" role="img" loading="lazy"
    
    alt="Concept map situating data physicalization in relation to other types of data representations and interpretations."><figcaption>
        <p>Concept map situating data physicalization in relation to other types of data representations and interpretations.
        <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3261531">From the “Data Beyond Vision” poster presented at DH2019, Utrecht, July 2019.</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only" id="">
⩩&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;⟩
| FIGURE.
|
| CAPTION: Concept map situating data physicalization in relation to other types of data representations and interpretations.
| ATTRIBUTION: From the “Data Beyond Vision” poster presented at DH2019, Utrecht, July 2019.
| LINK: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3261531">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3261531</a>
⩩&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;⟩
</div>
<div class="sr-only" id="conceptmap-desc">
Other approaches for data representation and interpretation include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Data Visualization, which focuses on storytelling by using graphical elements</li>
<li>Data Edibilization, which focuses on experiencing data through food using edible materials</li>
<li>Data Sonification, which focuses on auditory patterns by using sound</li>
<li>Data Visceralization, which focuses on multiple sensory experiences by using multiple senses, making it the only approach that can incorporate all of the senses</li>
<li>Data Art, which focuses on representing links between data and artistic creations by using expressive frameworks and raw data.</li>
<li>Interpretive object, which focuses on revealing meanings and relationships via non-textual forms by using metaphors.</li>
</ul>
</div></p>
<p>Making use of other senses can provide a step towards greater accessibility. The typical solution for making data visualization accessible to vision-impaired readers is to provide a table with the data underlying the chart or graph. This isn’t practical for large datasets, and it’s clearly not the same experience, or otherwise we would provide the tabular data to all users. Another approach is to provide an extended description of the insights gained from the chart. This is helpful, but pre-digesting the chart in this way doesn’t allow readers to view and interpret the patterns and draw their own conclusions.</p>
<p>We invite you to participate in the labor of data work. Download models and instructions, use your hands to recreate the data physicalizations we developed, or use these as inspiration to make your own interpretive objects.</p>
<div class="icon-nav" id="">
<span class="help">Choose an object</span>
<a href="#folding"><img src="images/icon-folding.svg" alt="view folding section"></a>
<a href="#modeling"><img src="images/icon-printing.svg" alt="view modeling section"></a>
<a href="#weaving"><img src="images/icon-weaving.svg" alt="view weaving section"></a>
<a href="#stacking"><img src="images/icon-stacking.svg" alt="view stacking section"></a>
</div>
<h2 id="folding">Folding in the Non-Famous Members of the Shakespeare and Company Library</h2>

<div class="sketchfab-embed-wrapper">
    <iframe
        id="sketchfab-9c96fadd27c34a11902f0a1281ea0ab4"
        title="Shakespeare and Company membership origami on Sketchfab"
        frameborder="0"
        allow="autoplay; fullscreen; vr"
        mozallowfullscreen="true"
        webkitallowfullscreen="true"
        loading="lazy"
        src="https://sketchfab.com/models/9c96fadd27c34a11902f0a1281ea0ab4/embed?autospin=0.2&amp;autostart=0&amp;camera=0&amp;preload=1&amp;ui_controls=1&amp;ui_infos=1&amp;ui_inspector=1&amp;ui_stop=1&amp;ui_watermark=1&amp;ui_watermark_link=1">
    </iframe>
</div>

<h3 id="goal">Goal</h3>
<p>The Shakespeare and Company library is most often known by its famous members — the writers of the Lost Generation and their friends. We wanted to highlight the activity of the relatively unknown members — frequently women - who in fact represent a much larger portion of the library&rsquo;s day-to-day activity and thus arguably better represent it. The piece makes use of unit origami to create a larger, cohesive form from small folded units, mirroring the relationship between a single member and the greater bulk of the library.</p>
<h3 id="description">Description</h3>
<p>The physicalization contrasts the activity of the well-known members of the library (those linked by researchers to an entry in VIAF) with the activity of its relatively unknown members (no known authority records). Activity is represented by the total number of recorded events that would plausibly have brought members into the library - checking out, renewing, and returning books. By holding the physicalization in two different ways, the user can &ldquo;grasp&rdquo; two separate sets of data: the octahedron (non-famous members) and the cube (famous members). The ratio of the volumes of these two solids is equal to the ratio of the two datasets.</p>
<h3 id="insights">Insights</h3>
<p>A pie chart can be used to present the same ratio of data conveyed in the physicalization. &hellip;.</p>
<h3 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3>
<p>Using cut, punched, or embossed paper would make the piece more tactile; instead of simply printing names, unique patterns could be added to represent data for individual members. In the future, we could generate unique folding patterns for individual library member activity and make them available via print-on-demand, which would enable viewers to become participants and turn folding into an act of recovery of the unknown library members.</p>
<p>Nick Budak, Xinyi Li</p>
<div class="icon-nav" id="">
<span class="help">Choose an object</span>
<a href="#folding"><img src="images/icon-folding.svg" alt="view folding section"></a>
<a href="#modeling"><img src="images/icon-printing.svg" alt="view modeling section"></a>
<a href="#weaving"><img src="images/icon-weaving.svg" alt="view weaving section"></a>
<a href="#stacking"><img src="images/icon-stacking.svg" alt="view stacking section"></a>
</div>
<h2 id="modeling">Modeling Shakespeare and Company Library Membership</h2>

<div class="sketchfab-embed-wrapper">
    <iframe
        id="sketchfab-89985d66f7244d87b7edbe5fd6266f0d"
        title="Shakespeare and Company membership lollipop chart on Sketchfab"
        frameborder="0"
        allow="autoplay; fullscreen; vr"
        mozallowfullscreen="true"
        webkitallowfullscreen="true"
        loading="lazy"
        src="https://sketchfab.com/models/89985d66f7244d87b7edbe5fd6266f0d/embed?autospin=0.2&amp;autostart=0&amp;camera=0&amp;preload=1&amp;ui_controls=1&amp;ui_infos=1&amp;ui_inspector=1&amp;ui_stop=1&amp;ui_watermark=1&amp;ui_watermark_link=1">
    </iframe>
</div>

<h3 id="goal-1">Goal</h3>
<p>This data physicalization demonstrates the affordances of three dimensions for representing data: time series data are displayed with sequential months and years adjacent to each other, which makes it easier to discern seasonal and annual trends. I hope to inspire others to try experimental approaches to representing data; writing software to generate printable 3D models directly from the data makes the process reproducible, and may eventually enable others to create and print their own physicalizations. The tactile nature of the object suggests the possibilities of 3D printing to create more accessible representations of data.</p>
<h3 id="description-1">Description</h3>
<p>This is a two variable, three dimensional lollipop chart showing the membership of the Shakespeare and Company library by month and year, from November 1919 when Sylvia Beach opened her bookstore to its official closing in 1942. Membership data is drawn from two different sources, both of which are incomplete: broad subscription information comes from <a href="https://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/sources/logbooks/">logbooks</a> (although logbooks for 1930 and parts of 1931-32 are missing); detailed borrowing histories come from <a href="https://shakespeareandco.princeton.edu/sources/cards/">lending library cards</a> for a subset of members. The white represents the number of members with an active subscription in each month; the green<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> corresponds to the number of members with borrowing activity in each month. For any month where the value is zero, there is no lollipop. Representing the two different datasets as adjacent half lollipops exposes the discrepancies between the stories these sources tell us about the membership of the library without privileging either of them. The two lollipop charts are designed to be printed independently and then assembled, so that any 3D printer can be used; however, this is a prototype and the design needs further revision.</p>
<h3 id="insights-1">Insights</h3>
<p>The same data can be presented in a two-variable bar chart. Overall trends are easy to see, but seasonal trends are not as distinct. Changing perspective on the physical object allows focusing on yearly or monthly trends. Missing data in one variable is visible in both &hellip; [TBD]<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="next-steps-1">Next Steps</h3>
<p>The current version uses different shapes for the two variables, but adding textures would make the model even more tactile. Simple 3D labels with text and braille have been added for display alongside the piece, but perhaps they could incorporated directly on the model, and refined to provide a scale for the axes. The 3D printed objects could also be augmented with other media: lights or sound could convey intensity of borrowing activity, or threads connecting months to represent the number of subscription renewals and convey a sense of continuity. The Python code used to create these models could be generalized for reuse, and eventually made available as a Blender plugin.</p>
<p>Rebecca Sutton Koeser</p>
<div class="icon-nav" id="">
<span class="help">Choose an object</span>
<a href="#folding"><img src="images/icon-folding.svg" alt="view folding section"></a>
<a href="#modeling"><img src="images/icon-printing.svg" alt="view modeling section"></a>
<a href="#weaving"><img src="images/icon-weaving.svg" alt="view weaving section"></a>
<a href="#stacking"><img src="images/icon-stacking.svg" alt="view stacking section"></a>
</div>
<h2 id="weaving">Weaving Derrida’s references</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>… we all of us, grave or light, get our thoughts entangled in metaphors…
<cite> George Eliot, Middlemarch</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="goal-2">Goal</h3>
<p>With this piece, we aim to literalize the metaphor of weaving as writing by representing Derrida’s intertextuality as a woven tapestry. The textures of the yarn and woven fabric invite touch, but by showing an in-progress weaving with the pattern and instructions provided, we move viewers beyond seeing and touching to enable them to become participants in reconstructing the data. Showing the weaving in progress also foregrounds the labor of data work, since curation, collection, and visualization all take an enormous amount of work and skill, often from a range of different individuals.</p>











 








<figure>
    
    <img src="/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" role="img" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100%, 80%" loading="lazy" 
    srcset='/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 500w,
    /issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
    /issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
    /issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
    /issues/1/data-beyond-vision/images/weaving_photo_hu922073d4c6e051c7a1adf75197e5e77d_1859719_1800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1800w,
    '
    class="portrait"
    
    alt="Setting up the warp on the loom to start weaving."><figcaption>
        <p>Setting up the warp on the loom to start weaving.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="txt-only" id="">
Photo. [TBD. Whatever level of description (if any!) we want here.]
</div>
<h3 id="description-2">Description</h3>
<p>This weaving represents the references in chapter one of Jacques Derrida’s de la Grammatologie. The references have been cataloged and categorized by researchers for Derrida’s Margins. Each type of reference (epigraph, citation, quotation, footnote) is represented by a distinct yarn and weaving pattern. Derrida’s highly intertextual writing suggested the idea of weaving, and using yarn to symbolize the foundational work of deconstructionism, which operates by finding the place where a text unravels, gives additional depth to this physicalization. Textile work is often stereotyped as women’s work, so this piece also raises questions of gender, art versus craft, and high tech versus low tech.</p>
<div class="deepzoom" id="openseadragon-11" style="height: 10em"></div>
<script>
    window.addEventListener("DOMContentLoaded", function() {
        OpenSeadragon({
            id: "openseadragon-11",
            prefixUrl: "https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/openseadragon@2.4/build/openseadragon/images/",
            preserveViewport: true,
            visibilityRatio:    1,
            minZoomLevel:       1,
            defaultZoomLevel:   1,
            gestureSettingsMouse: { scrollToZoom: false },
            tileSources: "https:\/\/iiif.princeton.edu\/loris\/iiif\/2\/figgy_prod%2F58%2F51%2Fd4%2F5851d48b225b42699a13181c778a6095%2Fintermediate_file.jp2\/info.json",
        });
    });
</script>
<h3 id="insights-2">Insights</h3>
<p>[tbd]</p>
<h3 id="next-steps-2">Next Steps</h3>
<p>Adding conductive thread and sensors could turn the weaving into an interface, so that touching the fabric would bring up the relevant reference on an associated screen. Data weavings could also be augmented with other media, such as lights and sound to convey other aspects of the same or related data. Incorporating other work on automated weaving and knitting machines would add to the variety of options for data textiles.</p>
<p>Rebecca Sutton Koeser, Gissoo Doroudian</p>
<div class="icon-nav" id="">
<span class="help">Choose an object</span>
<a href="#folding"><img src="images/icon-folding.svg" alt="view folding section"></a>
<a href="#modeling"><img src="images/icon-printing.svg" alt="view modeling section"></a>
<a href="#weaving"><img src="images/icon-weaving.svg" alt="view weaving section"></a>
<a href="#stacking"><img src="images/icon-stacking.svg" alt="view stacking section"></a>
</div>
<h2 id="stacking">Stacking New and Continuing Membership Activities of Shakespeare and Company Library</h2>
<h3 id="goal-3">Goal</h3>
<p>This piece aims to reveal the continuity and growth of Sylvia Beach’s lending library by showing the extent of activity and recorded membership based on logbooks and lending cards. Multiple variables are encoded in the dimensions of stacking boxes based on the technique of pop-up box folds. By exhibiting the evolution of the library over time while contrasting activities of new and old patrons, this piece enables multiple ways to compare and interpret the data from diverse perspectives. By transforming a flat surface to a three-dimensional form with play of light and shadows, this production technique serves as a metaphor for the purpose of larger Shakespeare and Company Project— bringing archival data to life and facilitating rich interpretations<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="description-3">Description</h3>
<p>Shakespeare and Company Project library membership data from 1919 to 1941 are represented as a hybrid of time-series and stacked bar charts showing part-to-whole relationship made from paper and folding. Each unit, a cuboid in space and sometimes its stacking child, represents one year and displays nine variables for that year. The height corresponds to the number of active subscribers recorded in the logbooks; the depth depicts the number of members with borrowing activity, according to each member’s lending library card; the length along the timeline is based on the total number of borrowing events. Each of the variables is split into two parts: previous patrons who have renewed a subscription contrasted with new members. The upper portion shows the growth and the activities of new readers. Viewers can see the rise and fall of subscribers, inspect the difference between active borrowers and subscribers, compare the growth over time by viewing the stacking part from the front, and survey the involvement of continuing members versus new patrons, to name a few possibilities. In some cases, a small number of new members were very active readers based on their borrowing activity. Data was mapped to the shapes with Data Illustrator, semi-manual calculation and vector drawing.</p>
<h3 id="insights-3">Insights</h3>
<p>[tbd]</p>
<h3 id="next-steps-3">Next Steps</h3>
<p>The data encoding process could be automated by writing custom code, which could then be made available as a tool for presenting part-to-whole relationships. With the addition of time-based media such as projection mapping, this piece could convey more context and narratives around the lending library.</p>
<p>Xinyi Li</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Staley, David. “On the ‘Maker Turn’ in the Humanities.” In <em>Making Things and Drawing Boundaries</em>, edited by Jentery Sayers, 32–41. Experiments in the Digital Humanities. University of Minnesota Press, 2017. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctt1pwt6wq.5">https://doi.org/10.5749/j.ctt1pwt6wq.5</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Test short note. <a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>We use white and green in our physicalizations of data from the Shakespeare and Company Project because those are the two main colors used in the site design. <img src="images/scp_colors_dark.png" alt="color palette from Shakespeare and Company Project"> <a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Test note with image. <img src="images/icon-folding.svg" alt="view folding section"> <a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Test really long note. Viewers can see the rise and fall of subscribers, inspect the difference between active borrowers and subscribers, compare the growth over time by viewing the stacking part from the front, and survey the involvement of continuing members versus new patrons, to name a few possibilities. In some cases, a small number of new members were very active readers based on their borrowing activity. Data was mapped to the shapes with Data Illustrator, semi-manual calculation and vector drawing. <a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">Their Data, Ourselves: Illness as Information</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/their-data-ourselves/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/their-data-ourselves/</id><author><name>Rebecca Munson</name></author><published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T12:29:28-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I was growing up I liked to read about dying children. I’m not talking about the Victorian orphan kind of dying, not the dying of storybooks, but children who were terminally ill.</p>
<p>I was twelve and fixated on books written by an author with the improbable name of Lurlene McDaniel. The first book I encountered was <em>Six Months to Live</em>, which chronicled the life of a popular teenager in the wake of her diagnosis with leukemia. McDaniel&rsquo;s characters didn&rsquo;t just have cancer; they wrestled with all kinds of chronic illnesses (cystic fibrosis, hemophilia, diabetes) as well as the untimely death of loved ones from causes including suicide. They were books about grief and communities formed through crisis.</p>
<p>These books would have been perfect for a budding hypochondriac, or for a reader inclined towards purple prose and melodrama, but I read them instead for medical details, taking mental notes on how to recognize signs and symptoms and stockpiling already-outdated knowledge about treatment options. Rather than imagining myself as the sick main character, I occupied the position of the doctor, a role I planned (at the time) to take on later in real life. It turned out, though, that I would have to be the protagonist anyway.</p>
<p>I was diagnosed with Stage 4 breast cancer in January 2019. I was thirty-four at the time, with zero family history and no warning signs aside from the lump I hoped fervently would be a cyst. Immediately, I was launched into a world at once familiar and alien. I had grown up among doctors and research scientists in the orbit of Washington University Medical School, largely because my father is a medical ethicist with an abiding interest in the practical applications of his work. I had even worked in a research laboratory there from ages sixteen to twenty, studying&mdash;of all things&mdash;the genetics of breast cancer.</p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    …my best chance at coping with cancer was to make sure I was a research subject, to transform my body as rapidly as possible into the right kind of data.
</blockquote>
<p>Is it any wonder, then, that I explored my treatment options as though I were the PI on an exploratory grant rather than a cancer patient? The type of breast cancer I have (triple negative) is particularly rare and intractable. At the time of my diagnosis it had already progressed to its most advanced stage with metastases to lungs, liver, and bones. It was immediately clear that finding promising clinical trials would be my best option. My parents and I (all academics) and circle of friends (ditto) kicked into research mode, scouring databases and firing off emails to friends from conferences, people from our past, even casual acquaintances who might have a line on newer, more successful treatments. The numbers were not good. We wanted some better numbers.</p>
<p>As I made phone calls to oncologists and combed through the clinical trials database, I performed a distancing maneuver that I first began practicing when reading Lurlene McDaniel; I became a clinical observer of a diseased body, only this time it was my own. I mentally dissected it, narrowing it down to the cancerous focal points that became all that mattered. I lay repeatedly in CT and MRI machines and held my breath through biopsies with only local anesthetics, willing myself out of the body I was at the same time trying so hard to save.</p>
<p>I became at once both object and analyst, alienating my self (with her feelings about her body and her illness) from my body as a source of information about potential causes and, hopefully, potential cures. In some ways it was the extreme of Cartesian dualism, I would think as the large magnets in the MRI machine echoed all around me, that my consciousness should roam so freely while I tried my hardest not to move a muscle in order to produce as clear an image of my body as possible. I was the mind-body problem made flesh, and then abstracted from flesh into numbers that could either be parsed by a machine or interpreted by a human.</p>
<p>Where did this data sit on the spectrum of mental and physical properties? My cancer was physical but, like an electron or snippet of DNA, it was not directly observable without the aid of technologies nor communicable without the intervention of an interpreter. In each of the two trials in which I&rsquo;ve been a subject I have contributed both pieces of my body&mdash;samples of tissue to be used at the discretion of researchers&mdash;and data generated from it. As a participant in clinical trials the status of my embodied data possesses an enduring significance, since it has the potential to influence the funding and availability of future cancer therapies, even the lifespan of future patients.</p>
<p>We all agreed that my best chance at coping with cancer was to make sure I was a research subject, to transform my body as rapidly as possible into the right kind of data: not a mortality statistic but an experimental resource.</p>
<hr>
<p>Cancer is invisible and so are data.</p>
<p>Neither exists in the sense of being detectable, nameable, or identifiable until plucked from their surroundings and marked out with a significance determined by the observer. The observer marks a data point as distinctive, distinguishing &ldquo;that&rdquo; from the &ldquo;not-that&rdquo; of everything around it. Even if a data point is meant to be representative, to stand in for a larger phenomenon, the act of selecting it renders it distinctive. The data you select&mdash;and the data you don&rsquo;t&mdash;say something about you as well as about them. Data are not objective phenomena. It is for this reason that digital humanities scholar Johanna Drucker has suggested that it is perhaps more accurate to think of data as <em>capta</em> to indicate their situatedness&mdash;that they are seized and, from the moment of demarcation, imbued with an interpretive viewpoint.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>The introduction of the interpretive viewpoint in medicine is called diagnosis. During the initial diagnostic phase, as I received phone call after phone call with more bad news, I spent some time thinking about how &ldquo;diagnosis&rdquo; sounded like a term familiar to me from my PhD in Renaissance literature, one that showed up mostly in discussions of tragedies: anagnorisis, meaning &ldquo;recognition,&rdquo; referring to the moment of a critical discovery about a character&rsquo;s own circumstances.</p>

<blockquote class="pull right">
    Any promise of transparency or intelligibility must be counterbalanced by the knowledge that all data have a viewpoint because they have an observer.
</blockquote>
<p>You will not recognize that you have cancer until someone tells you. You may have a suspicion that something is not quite right, but you require professional assessment. Assessment comes in the form of quantification, which requires abstraction. Your physical body is transformed into radiological images by technologies that allow trained specialists to measure and quantify, to compare averages and standard variations, and to relay that information back to you in language that leads, invariably, to another set of numbers concerned with averages and likelihoods. Where is the line between &ldquo;normal&rdquo; and &ldquo;pathological&rdquo;? In whose view is a treatment &ldquo;better&rdquo; or &ldquo;worse&rdquo;? When the questions are of life and death, it is more than a little disconcerting to realize that the answer depends very much upon who you&rsquo;re asking.</p>
<p>Cancer exists before it is named, just like data. And even at its moment of detection (capture) its fixity is illusory: it is in cancer&rsquo;s nature to grow and change, just like data. The moment of visibility for both is firmly situated in time, place, and the subject position of the interpreter. Take, for example, the open question of how extensively cancer may have spread to my liver. Unusually for my age, I was actually tested for cancer in 2016, in search of answers to a years-long chronic fatigue for which I still have no good explanation. The bone marrow biopsy showed no cause for concern and even though there was a lesion on my liver, measuring 29mm x 28mm, the conclusion was that it was a benign growth called a hemangioma. (I stand by this view, if only because a cancerous growth on my liver, a canary in a coal mine, would have become significantly worse over the course of three years given how aggressive cancer has been elsewhere in my body in the time since my diagnosis.)</p>
<p>My first CT after diagnosis in January 2019 showed the liver lesion to be 29mm x 35mm, a finding that the radiologist remarked might represent growth (and therefore metastasis) or might not, since a difference of 6mm could be caused by different positioning during the scan or different measurements by different doctors. The lesion continued to remain stable on my next CTs, but in March 2019 an additional spot was detected on the right inferior lobe, measuring 12mm. By June 2019 that spot was reported to be 28mm, confirming that my liver had been affected. In December the second lesion was measured under 5mm, part of a larger pattern of regression that meant the treatment was working (which it had done but would not continue to past that month). A third spot on the left lobe was recorded in three scans, showing up as 5mm August 2019, 4mm in September, and 3mm in November. By December that third spot went unremarked. The large lesion from 2016, however, merely waxed and waned, never clocking in at more than 35mm or fewer than 27mm, numbers easily attributable to variation in imaging or interpretation.</p>
<p>So was the original liver lesion a benign hemangioma, a coincidence unrelated to the cancer that would metastasize years later, or the first sign that a breast cancer concealed in single, unmassed (and therefore undetectable) cells had already done so? Did the 2016 scan produce bad data, or rather bad capta? Was the interpretation of the image biased by the fact that I was young (31) and, aside from mysterious, debilitating fatigue, healthy? Should I have acted differently? Should my doctors? The ramifications of these questions for my diagnosis and emotional response to it are profound: a cancer that had been present since 2016 would look relatively less aggressive compared to one that was new as of 2019; being misdiagnosed and living with cancer for three years would compound my fear (and guilt) that my situation was preventable.</p>
<p>There is no way to know, though the probability is strong that the first lesion was and remains benign. But that uncertainty is the constant condition of the body as data. Any promise of transparency or intelligibility must be counterbalanced by the knowledge that all data have a viewpoint because they have an observer.</p>
<hr>
<p>In <em>The Undying</em>, her account of treatment for triple-negative breast cancer, the poet Anne Boyer writes that &ldquo;a patient is a system-containing object within a series of interlocking systems full of other system-containing objects&rdquo; and that &ldquo;to take a thing or set of things from one system and reclassify these as elements in another also resembles diagnosis, which takes information from our bodies and rearranges what came from inside us into a system imposed from far away.&quot;<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> Cancer is caused by the body&rsquo;s own cells growing out of control, a hostile takeover from within that violates the rules of the system already in place. Reclassified, your own cells are a disease and your own body a weapon. Reclassified, you are not an individual but a patient and your body not a collection of sensations but a rich mine of information.</p>

<blockquote class="pull left">
    Living your life as medical data is an alienating experience particularly if, like me, you look bad on paper.
</blockquote>
<p>Once you enter the systems of modern medicine you become data to be ingested, part of the larger dataset of those who have previously been ill, been treated, and lived or died. This is not the &ldquo;violence of abstraction&rdquo; of which Marxist theorists wrote, yet the phrase seems equally applicable to the anonymity&mdash;the interchangeability&mdash;of those subsumed by the medical-industrial complex. Part of the reason that I sought clinical trials was that I felt that it was the best way to enable physicians to see me as an individual whose life, and whose treatment, mattered. I was eager to make myself an object of study and contribute to thwarting the disease that is threatening my life. But I was equally eager not to be simply tagged, processed, and swept through the prescribed (and not very promising) series of treatments that constituted the &ldquo;standard of care&rdquo; for my type of cancer.</p>
<p>Living your life as medical data is an alienating experience particularly if, like me, you look bad on paper. Boyer describes herself as &ldquo;a patient made of information, produced by the work of women,&rdquo; remarking on the &ldquo;paradoxical simultaneity&rdquo; of the care work and data work performed by the overwhelmingly female nursing staff in their interactions with patients.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> It is crucial to focus on the significance of the word &ldquo;made&rdquo; here. None of us exist as free-floating data points; medical data are <em>made</em>, are in fact <em>capta</em> that depend on nurses and technicians, radiologists and pathologists, and, perhaps most of all, on patients.</p>
<hr>
<p>Cancer is invisible, and so are viruses.</p>
<p>I have worked on this essay over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic. I began it in March 2020, days after my workplace went remote and 14 months after my initial cancer diagnosis. It is now October 2020, my third line of treatment has failed, and I am moving onto another. The pandemic still ravages much of the country. Conceiving of bodies as &ldquo;made of information&rdquo; (and participating in the quantification of illness and the violence of abstraction that accompanies this process) has become a national way of life.</p>
<p>I have lived nearly two years tolerating the same kind of existential uncertainty and fear of an alien invader in the body that the world as a whole is now experiencing. I have played my own doctor, watching my body for signs that a treatment is working, or that it is not, in much the same way we monitor ourselves for symptoms. I have tried to anticipate what will happen if I become severely immunocompromised and have given up many of the pleasures that made my life better before (traveling, going out with friends) in the name of my health. I have offered my body up as data to research scientists with the goal of furthering not just my own treatment but survival prospects for the future.</p>
<p>I did not know that I was in training for a time when we would all of necessity be regarded as bodies with the potential to produce valuable data about the spread and effects of COVID-19. We are constantly starved for numbers, for data on infections and recoveries and for statistical models that may relieve us of the uncertainty we feel about the future. I cannot provide that. But I can tell you to be cautious readers of data and statistics that speak with any pretense to authority right now, even though I crave them too.</p>
<p>We are in the middle of the data. Some of us clamor loudly to be heard, to be seen and counted by institutions that deliberately overlook and under-report. For some of us, visibility entails vulnerability and the threat of unemployment or detainment weighs so heavily that illness must remain invisible, ignored or hidden. We are the data, but we do not always speak for ourselves.</p>
<p>Susan Sontag wrote in <em>Illness as Metaphor</em> that &ldquo;Everyone who is born holds dual citizenship, in the kingdom of the well and in the kingdom of the sick. Although we all prefer to use only the good passport, sooner or later each of us is obliged, at least for a spell, to identify ourselves as citizens of that other place.&quot;<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> A pandemic transcends borders but does not do away with the kingdom of the sick. As someone already resident, I can say to you: welcome. The hardest thing about being here is the grief for what we have lost, including a sense of normalcy. The best thing, though, is what we may find: community in a time of crisis.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Drucker, Johanna. &ldquo;Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display.&rdquo; <em>Digital Humanities Quarterly</em> 005, no. 1 (March 10, 2011). <a href="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Boyer, Anne. <em>The Undying: Pain, Vulnerability, Mortality, Medicine, Art, Time, Dreams, Data, Exhaustion, Cancer, and Care</em>. New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2019. p. 65 and 14. <a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Boyer, 55. <a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
<p>Sontag, Susan. <em>Illness as Metaphor</em>. New York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1978. p. 3. <a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">Stack Shakespeare and Company Membership Activities</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/stack-shakespeare-and-company-membership-activities/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/stack-shakespeare-and-company-membership-activities/</id><author><name>Xinyi Li</name></author><author><name>Rebecca Sutton Koeser</name></author><published>0001-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T12:29:28-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Create your own kirigami model of Shakespeare and Company lending library membership activities,
as described in <a href="/issues/1/data-beyond-vision/#stacking">Data Beyond Vision</a>.</p>
<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>
<ul>
<li>Printer</li>
<li>X-acto knife or other blade</li>
<li>Bone folder or credit card</li>
<li>Cutting matt or old magazines</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="supplies">Supplies</h2>
<ul>
<li>4 Sheets of card stock paper (letter size is recommended, larger also works)</li>
<li>Double-sided tape (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="steps">Steps</h2>
<ol>
<li>Download the PDF</li>
<li>Print on cardstock paper at actual size</li>
<li>Cut along the vertical solid lines</li>
<li>Fold along the horizontal dotted lines. Follow the legend for mountain and valley folds.</li>
<li>Set up on a table or shelf</li>
<li>For best results, set on a table against a wall and use double-stick tape to fix to table and wall surface (optional)</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Yield:</strong>  kirigami model of Shakespeare and Company lending library membership activities</p>
]]></content></entry><entry><title type="html">Weaving as interface</title><link href="https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/weaving-as-interface/?utm_source=atom_feed" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://startwords.cdh.princeton.edu/issues/1/weaving-as-interface/</id><author><name>Rebecca Sutton Koeser</name></author><author><name>Gissoo Doroudian</name></author><published>0001-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T12:29:28-04:00</updated><content type="html"><![CDATA[<html>
<head>
<title>deepzoom experiment</title>
<script src=https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/openseadragon@2.4.2/build/openseadragon/openseadragon.min.js integrity="sha256-NMxPj6Qf1CWCzNQfKoFU8Jx18ToY4OWgnUO1cJWTWuw=" crossorigin="anonymous"></script>
<!--<link rel="stylesheet" href-"https://derridas-margins.princeton.edu/static/CACHE/css/output.fd22c024c95d.css" type="text/css"/> -->
<style>
    body {
        background-color: black;
    }

    .highlight {
        /*border: 3px solid yellow;*/
    }
    .highlight:hover {
        border: 3px solid yellow;
    }

    .pnum {
        text-decoration: none;
        color: white;
        font-size: 22pt;
    }
/*    .pnum::after {
        content: '1';
        font-size: 22pt;
        display: block;
        color: white;
    }
*/

    .reference {
        position: absolute;
        padding: 20px;
        left: 0;
        bottom: 0;
        width: 450px;
        height: 350px;
        background-color: white;
        z-index: 3;
        opacity: 0;

       -webkit-transition: opacity 1.5s ease-in-out;
       -moz-transition: opacity 1.5s ease-in-out;
       -ms-transition: opacity 1.5s ease-in-out;
       -o-transition: opacity 1.5s ease-in-out;
    }

    .reference.loading {
        opacity: 0.5;
    }

    .reference.show {
        opacity: 1;
    }

</style>
</head>
<body>
<div class="reference"></div>

<div class="deepzoom" id="openseadragon-2" style="height:90vh"></div>

<!-- page numbers to overlay -->
<!-- TODO: generate these and the overlays with code -->
<div class="pages">
    <span id="p1">1</span>
    <span id="p2">2</span>
    <span id="p3">3</span>
    <span id="p4">4</span>
    <span id="p5">5</span>
    <span id="p6">6</span>
</div>


<!-- needed to make this work

- resolve CORS issue with derrida's site references
- styles for reference cards within this site
- touch events (hide reference card)

- may need to adjust zoom / pan per device (mobile)

- mobile style for reference card overlay

-->


<script>

var viewer = OpenSeadragon({
    id:"openseadragon-2",
    prefixUrl:"https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/openseadragon@2.4/build/openseadragon/images/",
    preserveViewport: true,
    visibilityRatio: 1,
    // disallow zoom in/out
    minZoomLevel: 5,
    maxZoomLevel: 5,
    defaultZoomLevel: 5,
    // disable vertical panning
    panVertical: false,
    showNavigationControl: false,

    tileSources:"https:\/\/iiif.princeton.edu\/loris\/iiif\/2\/figgy_prod%2F58%2F51%2Fd4%2F5851d48b225b42699a13181c778a6095%2Fintermediate_file.jp2\/info.json",
    overlays: [

        {
            // page1 label
            id: 'p1',
            px: 2600,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },

        {
            id: 'p2',
            px: 3793,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },
        {
            id: 'p3',
            px: 4840,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },
        {
            id: 'p4',
            px: 5862,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },
        {
            id: 'p5',
            px: 6210,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },
        {
            id: 'p6',
            px: 6570,
            py: 650,
            width: 50,
            height: 50,
            className: 'pnum'
        },

        {
            // epigram p15
            id: 'ref15a',
            px: 2560,
            py: 848,
            width: 352,
            height: 1776,
            className: 'highlight'
        },
        {
            // footnote 1 p16
            id: 'ref16a',
            px: 4359,
            py: 810,
            width: 141,
            height: 1794,
            className: 'highlight'
        },
        {
            // footnote 2 p16
            id: 'ref16b',
            px: 4500,
            py: 810,
            width: 141,
            height: 1794,
            className: 'highlight'
        },
        {
            // footnote 3 p16
            id: 'ref16c',
            px: 4642,
            py: 810,
            width: 141,
            height: 1794,
            className: 'highlight'
        },
    ],
})


viewer.addHandler("open", function () {
    console.log('opened');
    // start with left part of the weaving showing
    viewer.viewport.panTo(new OpenSeadragon.Point(0.17, 0.09), true)

    // equivalent event for touch?
    const referenceOverlays = document.querySelectorAll(".highlight");

    function showReference() {
        document.querySelector('.reference').classList.add('loading');

        console.log(this.getAttribute('id'));
        // var refID = references[this.getAttribute('id')];
        var refID = this.getAttribute('id').slice(3);
        var refUrl = '/references/de-la-grammatologie/' + refID + '/';
        // console.log(refUrl);
        console.log('https://derridas-margins.princeton.edu' + refUrl)
        // console.log('https://test-derrida.cdh.princeton.edu' + refUrl);
        // var xhr = new XMLHttpRequest();
        // xhr.onload = function() {
        //   console.log(this.responseXML.title);
        // }
        // xhr.open("GET", 'https://derridas-margins.princeton.edu' + refUrl);
        // xhr.responseType = "document";
        // xhr.send();

        fetch('https://derridas-margins.princeton.edu' + refUrl, {
        // fetch('https://test-derrida.cdh.princeton.edu' + refUrl, {
        // fetch('http://192.168.2.10:8000' + refUrl, {
            // headers: {
                // 'X-Requested-With': 'XMLHttpRequest',
            // }
        })
          // .then(response => console.log(response))
          .then(response => response.text())
          .then(function(text) {
            // console.log(data);
            // console.log(document.querySelector('.reference'));
            const ref = document.querySelector('.reference');
            console.log(text);
            ref.innerHTML = text;
            ref.classList.remove('loading');
            ref.classList.add('show');
          });
        }

    function hidereference() {
        const ref = document.querySelector('.reference');
        ref.innerHTML = '';
        ref.classList.remove('show');
    }

    for (const refOverlay of referenceOverlays) {
        refOverlay.addEventListener('touchstart', showReference)
        refOverlay.addEventListener('touchcancel', hidereference);

        refOverlay.addEventListener('mouseover', showReference)
        refOverlay.addEventListener('mouseout', hidereference);

    }

});

// viewer.addEventListener('open', function(event) {
    // console.log('binding hover listener for highlight');
// });

</script>
</body>
</html>]]></content></entry></feed>